<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unequal match, or, The life of Mary of Anjou Queen of Majorca  Part 1.  an historical novel.</title>
            <author>La Chapelle, M. de (Jean), 1655-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10966</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12425365</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12425365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61828</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47946)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61828)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 944:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unequal match, or, The life of Mary of Anjou Queen of Majorca  Part 1.  an historical novel.</title>
                  <author>La Chapelle, M. de (Jean), 1655-1723.</author>
                  <author>Spence, Ferrand.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 164 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Charles Blount ... and Richard Butt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: F.S. [i.e. Ferrand Spence]</note>
                  <note>Translation of the author's Marie d'Anjou, reigne de Maiorque, nouvelle historique et galante.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Queen, consort of Charles VII, King of France, 1404-1463.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61828:1"/>
            <p>THE Unequal Match: OR, THE LIFE OF MARY OF ANJOU QUEEN of MAJORCA. <hi>An Hiſtorical Novel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Charles Blount</hi> near the <hi>Bear Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern</hi> by the <hi>New Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Butt</hi> at the <hi>Bear</hi> and <hi>Orange-Tree</hi> in <hi>Princeſs Street</hi> near the <hi>Horſhoo-Tavern</hi> in <hi>Drury-Lane:</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:61828:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61828:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable THE Counteſs <hi>Dowager</hi> of <hi>Tenet,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen greatneſs is maintained and attended with all thoſe Gifts and Talents which procure it ecteem and reſpect, when Perſons of the higheſt Rank and Quality are more illuſtrious by their Merit than their Fortune, it is no wonder if the World flocks to them with Offerings, and that their excellencies procure them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times trouble and importunities inſtead of eaſe and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. All thoſe who have the Honour to know you, Madam, ſpeak even with that veneration of your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that I could not curb the Ambition I have of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one voice to the general ſhout, and from crowding up to your Feet, with this preſent. It is a Preſumption, Madam, I ſhould have deſpaired of ever having been able to have attoned for, had not this ſtory of the Queen of <hi>Majorca</hi> met with that approbation in the World,
<pb facs="tcp:61828:3"/>that it has been found capable of entertaining with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light the greateſt Judges, amongſt whom your Ladyſhip being with juſtice acknowledged to have the firſt Place, this Queen fancyed ſhe could be no where ſo ſafe as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo glorious a Protection, and therefore was reſtleſs and impatient, till I had <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhered and Introduced her into your Ladyſhips preſence. I ſhall have fully ſatisfied my vanity, if you find her Company, Madam, as agreeable as others have done, and if you can think fit to Pardon the dreſs ſhe appears in, which I'm afraid will be found to have too much of the <hi>French</hi> in it, and I in this a too Superſtitious obſerver of their Mode. But ſhould I excuſe my ſelf with her being huddled up in haſte, I ſhould but prove the more importunate; Nor ſhall I tell the World that Honour, Wit, and Vertue, have never had a better Example than your Ladyſhip, it would be I fancy like a Man in the Month of <hi>May</hi> or <hi>April,</hi> who in a clear, bright, Sun-ſhining Day, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a fair Proſpect of all the Beauties Nature was ever capable of beſtowing, and which were adorned by all manner of improvements, would declare to the World that it was Spring; and Figure to himſelf he had diſcovered a great ſecret, in publiſhing what was already the general delight, Admiration and Wonder: he could not fail of being ſimiled at for his folly, which to avoid, it is ſit that I be ſilent in a Subject that is above deſcription, that I make my Legg, and retire with all Submiſſion and Reſpect.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips moſt Obedient and moſt humble Servant. F. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61828:3"/>
            <head>MARY OF ANJOU, <hi>QUEEN</hi> OF MAJORCA.</head>
            <p>THe Caprichiousneſs of the Stars is much to be admired in the Deſtiny of Princeſſes, who ſeem to have been only born in an illuſtrious Rank, for to be the more unhappy; Policy uſually requiring, that they be delivered to Husbands without
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61828:4"/>conſulting their Inclinations; and that they be purely Victimes of State. <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Anjou,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> was a Famous Example of the fantasſticalneſs not to ſay of the injuſtice of the Stars. The King her Father gave her, or rather Sacrificed her to the King of <hi>Majorca.</hi> He had for her that tender affection, that the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed Princeſs upon the Earth merited; ſeverall Princes aſpired to ſo Illuſtrious a Poſſeſſion, and ſhe might have been happy. The King of <hi>Majorca</hi> was an Old Man, of a whimſicall and fierce humour: had already had two Wives, nay and had the Reputation of knowing how to diſpatch them when he pleaſed. An Union ſo ill ſuited, could not but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a very ill agreement. Yet all theſe reaſons tho' very powerfull, could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail in the mind of King <hi>Charles,</hi> over the reaſons of State; His Affairs demanded this Sacrifice from him, the King of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorca</hi> offered him great ſuccours by Sea, of which he had extream need for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the powerfull Fleet, that was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt him by <hi>Don James d' Arragon,</hi> out of whoſe Priſon he was newly relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61828:4"/>Inſomuch that he accepted that alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance preferrable to ſo many others, if not more illuſtrious, at leaſt more ſuitable to the Age and Humour of the Princeſs his Daughter, but which could not be then ſo uſefull to him, as that of the King of <hi>Majorca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall take the Subject a little farther than would be neceſſary for a Hiſtory of Gallantry, but as it is one of the fineſt Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the Hiſtory of <hi>Italy,</hi> and that I ſhall ſay nothing which does not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to a faithfull Hiſtorian, I aſſure my ſelf, that a Reader the leaſt curious, will not take ill my having added to the amou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Narration, a recitall of the paſſages of moſt importance in that time, and which will be no leſs diverting than what there was of Gallantry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the Second of that name, King of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> one of the greateſt Princes then under the Heavens, had been more than Ten Years free Poſſeſſour of thoſe two powerfull Kingdoms, when his ambition which could not contain it ſelf in the Narrow Bounds of ſome States, which made but a little part of the World, ſtirring up his Warlike Humour, inſpired
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61828:5"/>him with more glorious Conqueſts. <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> that Famous City, appeared to him a Subject worthy enough to make him take Arms, and ſome Lands he had in <hi>Morea,</hi> being capable of ſerving him for a reaſon, or at leaſt for a pretext to pretend to the Empire of the Eaſt: He prepared himſelf to drive away the Emperour <hi>Michael Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leologue,</hi> but fortune raiſed him on a ſudden greater Affairs than he could put an end to, and gave him in his own Country, wherewith to Exerciſe his Marſhall-Genius.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> according to their uſual Cuſtome lived in <hi>Sicily,</hi> with that Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty amongſt the Women they take in all places. Their Gallantry little agreable to the Humour of the Country, giving occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of complaints to ſeveral Husbands, there was one certain <hi>John de Procula,</hi> Phyſitian of the deceaſed King <hi>Manfroy,</hi> whoſe Crown <hi>Charles</hi> the Second then poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, who entertaining ſome ſecret Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligences with the Principal Lords of the Kingdom, reſolved to deliver his Country from ſo Incommode a Nation; He went for that end to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> had made known to the Emperour <hi>Michael</hi> the deſign that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61828:5"/>King <hi>Charles</hi> had, hoping to engage him by a Motive of revenge as well as of glory to favour the diſcontented party; but his practices not ſucceeding in that Court, which demanded nothing but Peace; and was not at the leaſt in a State of giving great ſuccours to the <hi>Sicilians,</hi> he paſſed into <hi>Catalonia,</hi> where he offered the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of the Iſle of <hi>Sicily,</hi> to <hi>Peter</hi> King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> who had Marryed <hi>Conſtance,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Manfroy,</hi> King of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily; Peter</hi> being an Ambitious Prince, and one of the moſt valiant of his time, puſht on by jealouſy of the Glory of <hi>Charles,</hi> as well as by Ambition, for ſo fair a Conqueſt: liſtened to the Propoſition of <hi>Procula,</hi> without ſeeming, however, to cloſe with it, till he firſt knew what the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Sentiments were therein, to whom this Phyſitian made two Journeys: And in fine after ſeveral Paces and Sollicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Reſolution being taken by <hi>Pietro d' Arragon, Nicholaus</hi> the Third, who then held the Pontificial See at <hi>Rome,</hi> gave him the inveſtiture of that <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What was moſt ſtrange in the ſucceſs of an Affair of ſo great an Importance, and at which Poſterity will have ever reaſon to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61828:6"/>be aſtoniſhed, is, that it was caried on with that Order and Secrecy for the ſpace of Eighteen Months, it was in Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that it could never come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of any <hi>French</hi> Man. Inſomuch that in one and the ſame day, at the firſt ringing of the Bell for Veſpers, generally all the Cities of that Kingdom took Arms, and made a horrible <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of all the <hi>French</hi> without any exception; And they were poſſeſſed to that Point, with hatred or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with fury againſt that Nation; that they put to the Sword, all the Women they found, that they beleived to be with Child by any <hi>French</hi> Man. This horrible Tragoedy happened in the Year, 1281. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Eleven Years after the Entire Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, in the two Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sicilians</hi> having thus cruelly freed themſelves from the <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Pietro d' Arragon,</hi> having taken poſſeſſion of the Iſland, <hi>Charles</hi> was forced to quit the vaſt deſigns he had on the Eaſt, to think of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſatisfaction for ſo cruel a Revolt; He prepared a powerfull Army againſt <hi>Sicily,</hi> and being come to beſeige <hi>Meſſina,</hi> he found the enterprize more difficult than he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61828:6"/>had beleived it. Inſomuch, that he was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to raiſe the Siege, and was repulſed as far as <hi>Calabria,</hi> from whence he went to <hi>Rome,</hi> to complain to the <hi>Pope</hi> of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtiture he had given to <hi>Pietro</hi> of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon,</hi> who in that time was Crowned at <hi>Palermo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Affair was agitated in full Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and the two Kings not agreeing, it was reſolved that it ſhould be decided by the way of Armes, between theſe two Princes; and this Duell, a thing very ſtrange, was even by the allowance of the Holy See. <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> the Capital City of <hi>Gaſcony,</hi> was choſen for the place of the Randevouz, and the King of <hi>England</hi> for Judge. Wherefore <hi>Charles</hi> came to the Place on the day aſſigned, and waited the greateſt part of the day for <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Arragon,</hi> who kept himſelf ſo well conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that no Body knew where he was, only it had been heard ſaid the day before, that he was ſtill ſo far from <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> that it was almoſt impoſſible, he could arrive there on the Day of aſſignation: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that <hi>Charles</hi> upon the going down of the Sun retired, and departed at the ſame time from <hi>Bourdeaux. Peter of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:61828:7"/>who had run inceſſantly upon good Horſes, that he had cauſed to be placed upon the ways, being arrived in <hi>cognito</hi> in the City, kept himſelf concealed till <hi>Charles</hi> was gon, and then he appeared in the Field of <hi>Battel,</hi> in the preſence of him who preſided there, being a Lord the King of <hi>England</hi> had ſent in his place, and complained of King <hi>Charles,</hi> whoſe Impatient Haughtineſs had not permitted him to attend his Arrival. He walked in that manner upon the place, till that he ſaw the Stars appear, than he remounted his Horſe, and returned with the ſame ſwiftneſs that he came, going, as is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Thirty Leagues that Night. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into a place of ſafety, thus deceiving King <hi>Charles;</hi> but <hi>Martin</hi> the Fourth, who was then <hi>Pope,</hi> excommunicated him, and conferred the Kingdom of <hi>Catalonia,</hi> on <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Valois,</hi> Second Son of <hi>Philip,</hi> King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the time that King <hi>Charles</hi> went to <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> for this Duell, <hi>Roger de Loria</hi> a <hi>Calabrian</hi> by Birth, Admiral of King <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Arragon,</hi> one of the moſt experienced as well as the braveſt Captains, that had e're been upon the Sea, plyed all the Coaſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61828:7"/>of <hi>Naples,</hi> with Forty Five Galleys, ruining all the Country, as far as the City of <hi>Naples,</hi> where he likewiſe came and ſhot an infinite number of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, reproaching the <hi>Neopolitans</hi> with Cowardice, defying them to come fight him. Which ſo ſtrongly animated a Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of brave men, there was in that City, and eſpecially the Young Nobility, that could not endure ſo cruel an affront, that <hi>Charles</hi> Prince of <hi>Salerno,</hi> the only Son of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, took the Reſolution of fighting him, notwithſtanding, all the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Legate, and the Expreſs Orders of the King his Father, who had recommended to him, to think only of well defending the City, and not to come to blows with the Enemies; This Prince, I ſay, puſhed on with a deſire of Glory, as well as Indignation at ſo injurious a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, went out with Thirty Galleys, and ſome other Veſſels of leſs Conſequence: and attacqued with more Valour than force <hi>Loria</hi>'s Fleet, who after a very ſharp fight, was at the length Conquerour, took Nine Galleys, and a great number of Young Lords, amongſt which was <hi>Charles</hi> Prince of <hi>Salerno,</hi> who was kept with Nine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61828:8"/>of thoſe he would chooſe, and the reſt were ſent to Priſon in <hi>Sicily,</hi> of whom, more than two Hundred were beheaded at <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſina,</hi> in revenge of the Death of <hi>Corradin,</hi> Young Prince of <hi>Suevia,</hi> whom King <hi>Charles</hi> whoſe Priſoner of War he was, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the cruel Sentence of <hi>Pope Clement</hi> the Fourteenth, a Provential by Birth, who wrote to him, <hi>Vita Corradini mors Caroli, mors Carradini vita Caroli;</hi> this King, I ſay, put him into the Hands of Juſtice, who condemned him to Death; A Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence however, which not only every <hi>French</hi> Lord and Gentleman refuſed to Sign, but whoſe Execution was fiercely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Count of <hi>Flanders,</hi> Son-in-Law to King <hi>Charles,</hi> ſaying that a Prince of that Blood was not to be put to Death after that manner: But to give him his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borty, and to make him rather a Friend, and an Ally, by the means of a Marriage.</p>
            <p>The Day after the defeat of the Prince of <hi>Salerno,</hi> the King his Father returning from <hi>Gaſcony,</hi> arrived at <hi>Gayeta,</hi> with Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Galleys, and Three great Ships with Soldiers and Horſes; and learnt the ſad News of his Sons misfortune, and that there was already a Revolt in the City of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:61828:8"/>all the People crying, may <hi>Roger de Loria</hi> live and <hi>Charles</hi> dye. At which this Prince fell into ſo great a Paſſion, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come near that City; he would not Land at the Port, but above the Church of the <hi>Carmelites,</hi> where he deſcended with deſign to ſet on fire that ungratefull and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious City. And was a long time in that cruel Reſolution, but at length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by the Tears of ſome good People, and by the Prayers of the Legate, he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned them, after having cauſed a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Fifty of the moſt culpable to be hanged. This puniſhment having both calmed and terrified the City, all his cares were to raiſe a powerfull Army, for to paſs into <hi>Sicily,</hi> which was ready about Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn; and he came to <hi>Cotrona</hi> with a Hundred and Ten Galleys, and ſome other Sails; but ſeeing the Winter come on, and wanting Victuals and Money for ſo great a Fleet, he went to diſarme at <hi>Brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſo,</hi> with deſign to put to Sea again in the Spring, and in the mean time to make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of all that ſhould be neceſſary for the bringing to paſs his Projects; If Death had not made them vaniſh in a moment. He dyed at <hi>Foggia,</hi> a City in <hi>la Pouille,</hi> oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61828:9"/>with ſadneſs and Malancholly, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lived Fifty Six Years, and reigned Nineteen. This Prince was tall, of a ruddy Complexion, had a great Noſe, and a fierce and Martial Air, he was ſharp and ſevere in puniſhment, much more admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for War than for Peace; As to the reſt, very ſerious, and of almoſt a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Life in what concerned Love. He ſlept little, ſpoak ſeldome, doing more than he ſaid; He was liberall to brave men, and firm in his Promiſes, an Enemy of Triſles and uſeleſs Courtiers, but a generous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectour of Soldiers, and Ambitious more than any Prince whatever, reſolute to have Money at any rate ſoever, when he was to bring to paſs any enterprize. One of the things that have been moſt found fault with, in this Prince, and which has leſt ſome ſtain in his Glory, is the great Licenſe, he gave to Soldiers in time of Peace, to the great diſadvantage of his Subjects; but otherwiſe, one of the moſt accompliſhed Princes of the Earth.</p>
            <p>In that time, <hi>Pope Martin</hi> had ſent two Cardinals to <hi>Sicily,</hi> for the endeavouring to make Peace with King <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and not being able to reduce him to accept
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61828:9"/>the Conditions that they propoſed, they renewed the Excommunication, there was againſt him; and likewiſe Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all <hi>Sicily,</hi> from whence they departed in that manner: The <hi>Sicilians</hi> more Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated than ever, to ſee themſelves ſo ill Treated by the <hi>Pope,</hi> in Conſideration of the <hi>French,</hi> having learnt the Death of King <hi>Charles</hi> run to the Priſons where the reſt of thoſe were who had been taken with the Prince of <hi>Salerno,</hi> for to <hi>Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre</hi> them: But they found there ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous a Reſiſtance, that for the ſparing of the Blood of theirs, they were Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſet the Priſon on Fire, and cauſed the Death by this unmercifull Cruelty of the fineſt Youth that had been ſeen of a long time in <hi>Italy,</hi> in ſequel of which they cauſed the Judges of the Principal Cities of the Kingdom to Aſſemble, for to make the Proceſs of the Prince of <hi>Salerno,</hi> who was in Priſon with Nine of his Friends, after the Example of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt who had cauſed <hi>Corradin</hi> to be thus judged, and they all unanimouſly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to be Beheaded, as had happened to the unfortunate Prince of <hi>Suevia;</hi> But Queen <hi>Conſtance,</hi> a Princeſs, whom Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61828:10"/>cannot enough commend, being then in <hi>Sicily,</hi> deſigned to ſave him, and for to ſatisfy the People, who demanded his Death, ſhe let them underſtand, that in an Affair of ſo great Importance, nothing could be Executed without the allowance of the King her Husband; and thereupon ſhe ordered, that that Prince ſhould be ſent into <hi>Catalonia,</hi> where King <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Arragon</hi> was, to the end he might do as he ſhould think convenient. This was at length approved by the People, and much Commanded in the World after the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pope</hi> having learnt the Death of this King, ſent to <hi>Naples,</hi> in Quality of Legate, <hi>Gerard</hi> Cardinal of <hi>Parma,</hi> and King <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Count de Artois</hi> his Son, for to take care of the State with <hi>Mary</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Salerno,</hi> in the Name of <hi>Charles</hi> then in Priſon; during that, this King on the other ſide with the <hi>Count de Valois,</hi> to whom the <hi>Pope</hi> had given the Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Catalonia,</hi> entred that Kingdom with two powerful Armies, of which that by Sea was of a Hundred and Twenty Galleys. They won <hi>Girona</hi> by aſſault, where the King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> who was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61828:10"/>there in Perſon to defend it, received a Wound, of which he dyed. He left <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus</hi> his Eldeſt Son King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and <hi>Don James</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Sicily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During that time, <hi>Roger de Loria,</hi> being departed from <hi>Sicily,</hi> to come to the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours of the King his Maſter, learnt that a part of the Fleet of <hi>France</hi> was in the Port of <hi>Roſes,</hi> and that the other was gon to ſeek Victuals at <hi>Narbonne.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he went and attacqued firſt that of <hi>Roſes,</hi> of which he burnt a part, having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or ſunk the reſt, and made Priſoner <hi>Enguiran</hi> Admiral of <hi>France.</hi> From thence turning towards that of <hi>Narbonne,</hi> he ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized and defeated it with much leſs dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty than the former, which being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by King <hi>Philip,</hi> who was Sick at <hi>Perpignan,</hi> it ſo grieved him, that it cauſed his Death; and almoſt at the ſame time that of <hi>Pope Martin</hi> the Fourth, Inſomuch that there dyed in the ſpace of a Year three Kings and a <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Things ſeemed to be ſome thing appeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the midſt of ſo many Deaths of that Conſideration, and the King of <hi>England,</hi> who was come into <hi>Gaſcony,</hi> endeavouring to make Peace between the two Young
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61828:11"/>Kings, <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, then in Priſon in <hi>Catalonia;</hi> had almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded when it was interrupted by the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I am going to relate.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal Legat, and the <hi>Count d' Artois,</hi> Governours of the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> judging the Conjuncture fair for the recovering of <hi>Sicily,</hi> reſolved with Fifty Galleys that they had obtained part from the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and part elſewhere, and ſome <hi>Militia,</hi> that they had cauſed to come from <hi>Toſcany</hi> with the <hi>French,</hi> and the Country People, to attempt this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize under the Command of <hi>Raynand, Count</hi> of <hi>Aveline.</hi> This Fleet put to Sea, they Landed in that Kingdom, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiged <hi>Catania,</hi> they took it, and the <hi>Count</hi> fortifying himſelf there, ſent his Fleet to <hi>Naples,</hi> for to take in the Soldiers which had been left on Shoar there. At the ſame time the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Montſort</hi> Vicar of <hi>Toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cany,</hi> accompanied with the <hi>Count de Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> Son of the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> who were at <hi>Sienna,</hi> departing from <hi>Maremma,</hi> with a Fleet of Sixty Galleys, of which <hi>Arrigin</hi> of <hi>Genoa</hi> was Admiral, came towards <hi>Sicily,</hi> to joyn with the <hi>Count
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61828:11"/>de Aveline.</hi> But <hi>de Loria,</hi> who had newly won two Famous Victories, having learnt at his coming from that of <hi>Narboune,</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent that the <hi>Nepolitans</hi> had made into <hi>Sicily,</hi> turned that way, and came to the Succours of the <hi>Sicilians.</hi> The Firſt that he met with, were thoſe of the <hi>Count de Aveline,</hi> who were going to <hi>Naples,</hi> whom he chaced, and finding them almoſt unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of Soldiers, he immediately routed them: and from thence going to meet that of the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Montfort,</hi> which was coming from <hi>Toſcany,</hi> there was a furious fight, in which being at length Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, he took the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Montfort</hi> Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Boulogne,</hi> and Prince <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip.</hi> Theſe two laſt ranſomed themſelves with a Sum of Money; But the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Montfort,</hi> having been detained Priſoner, dyed ſome time aſter in Priſon. Aafter theſe two Victories, <hi>Catania</hi> being beſeiged by all the Army of <hi>Arragon,</hi> without any hope of Succours, was obliged to render upon Compoſition, in the Articles of which it was permitted to the <hi>Count de Aveline,</hi> to retire to <hi>Naples,</hi> he and all thoſe who had accompanied him.</p>
            <p>The Treaty of Peace between theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61828:12"/>two Kings, that <hi>Edward</hi> of <hi>England</hi> had begun, having been interrupted upon this Subject, he brought it again up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Board, and infine concluded it upon Conditions much leſs favourable for <hi>Charles</hi> than the former, becauſe things had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly Changed Face, after the Victories that <hi>de Loria</hi> had won. King <hi>Charles</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and obliged himſelf to procure that the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Valois</hi> ſhould renounce all the pretentions that he might have upon <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia,</hi> by vertue of the Inveſtiture that <hi>Pope Martin</hi> the Fourth had given him of it; and that he would Labour at his own Charges, to make <hi>James</hi> King of <hi>Sicily</hi> be Crowned, who gave him three Years to acquit himſelf of theſe two Articles, for want of which <hi>Charles</hi> ſwore he would come again and put himſelf in Priſon at the End of that Term, in the ſame place where he was, and for ſurety of his word he gave to King <hi>james</hi> Three of his Sons in Hoſtage, who were <hi>Lewis</hi> ſince Biſhop of <hi>Tholoſe, Robert</hi> who ſucceeded his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Prince <hi>de la Morea,</hi> who dyed very Young, with whom King <hi>Charles</hi> their Father left. Fifty of the Braveſt Gentlemen, he had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61828:12"/>then with him. And Infine having more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over paid three Thouſand Marks of Silver in <hi>Carolins,</hi> he was delivered out of Priſon in the Year 1288, where he had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Four Years. He went immediately into <hi>France,</hi> to acquit himſelf of his word, and to procure of the <hi>Count de Valois,</hi> that he ſhould Renounce the Pretentions, he had upon <hi>Catalonia;</hi> But he could never obtain it, and departing from that Court, with a Number of Young Lords, and ſome Squadrons, which were under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Emerick de Narbonne,</hi> he came into <hi>Italy,</hi> paſſed through <hi>Perugia,</hi> where he ſaw <hi>Pope Nicholas</hi> the Fourth, who had ſucceeded <hi>Martin</hi> the Fourth, with whom having Treated of the renewing and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of his States; This <hi>Pope</hi> whether out of Imprudence, or Malice, for the Opinions are Divers therein, Intituled him King of both <hi>Sicilies,</hi> in the Year 1289, After which he went to <hi>Naples,</hi> where he was expected with the greateſt Impatience by all his Subjects, who had not ceaſed to make Vowes for his Liberty. But what was Extraordinary, and filled with joy and tenderneſs, the Hearts of thoſe who were there preſent, was to ſee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61828:13"/>the King with a Train of Young Lords, the moſt ſplendid and magnificent that had ever been beheld, and on the other ſide the Queen his Conſort who went Three Leagues out of the City to meet him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed with <hi>Charles Martel</hi> his Eldeſt Son, <hi>Philip</hi> Prince of <hi>Taranto</hi> his Fourth Son, and with Four Princeſſes his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; <hi>Blanehe, Eleonora, Mary,</hi> and <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, Clemence</hi> being marryed to the <hi>Count de Valois,</hi> all of them perfect Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and who had after them a Train of Young Princes, whom Glory and Love, Arms and Gallantry, diverſely engaged in that Court. It would be very diſſicult to expreſs the Joy that the King had at the ſight of the Queen and his Children; not being able to leave off Careſſing them, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the Princeſs <hi>Mary,</hi> for whom he had ever had a Particular tenderneſs, and who was ſo increaſed in. Beauty ſince his abſence that he could not enough admire her. The People of <hi>Naples</hi> received him with a joy and Acclamations that touched to very Tears: and the rejoycings upon his happy return, were ſuch as if fortune had ever been on their ſide. Thoſe Young Princes were ſeen to ſtrive to out doe one
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61828:13"/>another by their Addreſſes and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in the Turnaments; and all the other Feaſts which were dayly made: eſpecially thoſe who beſides Honour were Spirited with an Intereſt of Heart. Love Anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to ſupraſs all the others. All theſe Princeſſes were infinitely pretty; Yet as Palats are very different therein as in all other things, <hi>Mary</hi> according to the moſt Common Opinion, carried it from all the others, and as ſoon as ſhe approached her Siſters, ſhe ſeemed to Efface them. The Elogies that the Hiſtory of <hi>Italy</hi> give her, ſurpaſs all that can be believed. She had not only fine Eyes, a Noſe, and a Mouth, perfectly accompliſhed, Teeth extreamly white, a Shape, a Gate, an Air, a Port, a Majeſty worthy of the moſt lovely Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs upon the Earth; Her wit was likewiſe admirable in all kinds, a Grace in all ſhe did, as well as in all ſhe ſaid, that Charmed all People, and an underſtanding ſo fruitfull in all ſort of matters, that ſhe not only aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed but conſounded the moſt intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. So powerful Charmes hardly begun to appear, than that they had Adorers, and by the meaſure they increaſed, the number of her Gallants augmented alſo.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61828:14"/>Inſomuch that of all her Siſters, ſhe was the beſt provided by Love, as well as ſhe had been by Nature: There was reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt her votaries the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Boulogne,</hi> and Prince <hi>Philip,</hi> as thoſe who made the greateſt noiſe; after whom followed <hi>Az<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zo,</hi> Marqueſs <hi>d' Eſte,</hi> Prince of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Narbonne,</hi> Son of <hi>Emmeric,</hi> who endeavoured to attain to the magniſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, as well as Gallantry of the former; but a fifth who ſigh'd in ſecret for the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that Charming Princeſs, and who was the Lord of the Court, the moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally eſteemed, and the moſt welcome to the Ladies, was the Young <hi>Hamibal Count d' Aveline,</hi> Son of <hi>Raynand,</hi> one of the Gallanteſt men, and the beſt made of all <hi>Italy.</hi> The Glory and Rank of his Rivals had not hindred him to declare; his Heart was Young and ambitious, and would not have yielded to the Chiefeſt Princes of the Earth, but not ſeeing them more happy after their Declaration; and fearing a like Deſtiny with ſo haughty a Princeſs, he would manage her eſteem which he poſſeſſed, better the way he took, than any of his Rivals: His cares, his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duities, and his Complacency which he had
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61828:14"/>for her from the Morning to the Evening; were what ſpoke, and would have made her divine ſomething of what paſſed in his mind, if that Divine Princeſs, from whoſe Penetration nothing eſcaped, had not out of the goodneſs ſhe had for him, endeavoured to perſwade her ſelf the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that ſhe might not have reaſon to Treat him like the others, taking too much pleaſure in all the little Devoires he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred her, not to be troubled to give them another interpretation than that of the uſual Gallantry. However his Rivals who were very powerful with the King, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by their Quality, or by the Services they had rendred him, and which they were ſtill ready to render him, preſſed him very hard to declare himſelf in favour of ſome One, and the report was, his Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation was moſt for <hi>Philip</hi> the Son of the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Handers,</hi> which very much allar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all the others, and eſpecially <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> in whoſe Face was not only ſeen ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but Death Painted, from the time he heard talk of this Marriage. But the News which arrived, that King <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Arragon</hi> prepared to renew the War more hot than ever, giving other thoughts
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61828:15"/>and cares to King <hi>Charles,</hi> than thoſe of making Nuptials, were a great eaſe to the deſpair of theſe unhappy Rivals.</p>
            <p>This Prince, having learnt that King <hi>Charles,</hi> contrary to the Faith of the laſt Treaty, had cauſed the Pope to give him the Inveſtiture of the two <hi>Sicities,</hi> anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with hatred and reſentment, reſolved to be revenged, and made inceſſantly War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Preparations to go and attack him in his own Country; <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, as vigilant as a generous Prince, had not wanted foreſight, judging that his Enemy would not leave him long in Peace; He had Soldiers enough, but the loſſes that the Kingdom had had upon the Sea, while that he was in Priſon, in the two laſt Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters there had been, wherein <hi>Count Raynaud</hi> on the one ſide, and the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Montfort</hi> on the other, had been defeated, had ſo weakened him in that part, that all that the King had been able to do, ſince the little time he was returned to <hi>Naples,</hi> was to prepare a Fleet of Thirty Galleys, with which he could not pretend to ſhow himſelf againſt the Forces of the King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> who had more than Fourſcore Sail, under the Conduct of the Famous
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61828:15"/>
               <hi>Roger de Loria.</hi> However the time preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the News came that King <hi>James</hi> was arrived in <hi>Sicily,</hi> that by his Cabals he had cauſed part of <hi>Calabria</hi> to revolt, and that <hi>Catenzano</hi> had yeilded up to him, in ſo preſſing a neceſſity, his allies finding themſelves incommoded, or at leaſt diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented at the loſſes they had had in the two laſt Engagements, not to be able to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him ſo ſoon, he knew not what Councell to take, nor to whom to have recourſe, for the helping him to extinguiſh the Fire, which was juſt lighted in his own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, being more neceſſary for him to have forces by Sea to hinder the Succours of <hi>Sicily,</hi> than an Army by Land, in which he was ſtrong enough, when there appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Naples,</hi> Six Galleys which brought an Ambaſſador that the King of <hi>Majorca</hi> ſent to King <hi>Charles,</hi> to demand of him the Princeſs <hi>Mary</hi> in Marriage, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidedration of which he offered him Forty-Galleys, and Six Hundred Men at Armes, who were ready to ſet Sail at the firſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they ſhould have. This Ambaſſador was received with that Joy and Honour as ſo obliging offers merited, and which came ſo conveniently as thoſe did. It is true,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61828:16"/>that there was little Proportion between the Youth and the Qualities of that fair Princeſs, and the Age and Humour of this King; but the neceſſity of the time, and the advantage of an Alliance with a Prince ſo powerfull at Sea, and who becoming an Enemy by the refuſal that ſhould have been made him, would not have ſailed to have took the part of the <hi>Arragonians,</hi> were reaſons which prevailed over all the others, and over the particular tenderneſs the King had for that Princeſs; he propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Blanche</hi> or <hi>Eleonora,</hi> but the demand was expreſs for <hi>Mary,</hi> to the Excluſion of all the others. Inſomuch that in fine he was forced to reſolve of this Sacrifice, and the Affairs of the Kingdom, obliging the King to preſs the Concluſion of this Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, for the ſooner having the Succours, he expected it was almoſt as ſoon done as propoſed. The aſtoniſhment of all our Lovers, was as great as cruel: they had no ſooner learnt the Subject of that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy, than that they ſaw that <hi>Negotiation</hi> brought to an end. The King endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſatisfy the moſt Conſiderable, as the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Boulogne,</hi> Prince <hi>Philip,</hi> the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs d' Eſte,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Narbonne,</hi> there
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61828:16"/>being other fair Princeſſes enough in his. Family, for to repair that loſs, if that the Honour of his Allyance bound them to his Perſon; For <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s part, he had nothing but grief: from whoſe Succours he hoped to put quickly an end to his pains, at the ſame time with his life. But that which made him quite deſperate, was that the Princeſs who had more Confidence in him than in any other Lord of the Court, imparted to him part of her troubles, and the little ſatisfoction ſhe expected in this Marriage; complaining to him of the Cruelty of her Deſtiny, with Termes ſo touching the Soul of the ſad and paſſionate <hi>Hannibal,</hi> that notwithſtanding all the conſtraint he made upon himſelf, he could not hinder ſighing, without daring to look upon her, for fear his Eyes which he could not ſo well govern, as his mouth, ſhould have acquainted her with a ſecret, it was leſs time than ever ſhe ſhould know. The Fatal Day arrived at length, that ſhe was to depart, all the Court was to take leave of her, except the <hi>Count Hannibal,</hi> whom ſhe cauſed to be ſought for every where without being found. He even knew not, what was become of himſelf, ſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61828:17"/>much the greif of ſo Cruel a Separation: had put him beſides himſelf, he too well knew the weakneſs of his Heart, for to expoſe himſelf in the middle of all the Court, to bear ſo cruel a moment as that of the departure of that Charming Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, that the moſt indifferent could not ſee without Tears: He went out of the City, attended only by his Gentleman of the Horſe; and from the Sea Shoar, where he ſtayed, he ſaw the Galleys of <hi>Majorc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> depart with an immoveable Air, and almoſt without Sentiment, they carrying from him all that he had moſt dear in the World, without being able to retire from that Contemplation, ſo long as his ſight could accompany them.</p>
            <p>The City of <hi>Majorca,</hi> which bears the Name of the Iſleland, is one of the pret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyeſt Scituations in the <hi>Mediteranean Sea</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Belver</hi> Palace, where the Kings reſided, and which is a Work o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Antient <hi>Moors,</hi> half a <hi>League</hi> from the City, is one of the moſt lovely Place in the World. But to what uſe is the a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greableneſs of Places to a Young Princeſs if it be not joyned to that of Perſons She was hardly arrived there, than tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:61828:17"/>the King her Husband would ſend back the few People that accompanyed her, and this order was Executed, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the Oppoſition ſhe brought to it. So ſtrange a beginning could not fail of having ſad Conſequences. She quickly found a great difference between that gloomy and deſert Court, and that of the King her Father where all ſmiled, but ſeeing dayly ſome Change in the things that concerned her, and that her Liberty diminiſhed by the ſame degrees that her pains augmented, ſhe had many more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints to make. This Conduct appeared to her by ſo much the more rude, in that having been brought up in an Air of Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur and Liberty, Honoured, Served, and if it may be ſaid, adored by all the Princes and Lords at the Court of King <hi>Charles</hi> her Father, ſhe ſaw none about her but Old Women, who ſerved her ill enough, and ſhut up in Five or Six Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of her apartment, out of which ſhe could not go, without the Permiſſion of the King her Husband, and that even very rarely. What a Deſtiny for a Young and Fair Princeſs, whom the cheifeſt Kings of the Earth would have been
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61828:18"/>proud of ſerving, to ſee her ſelf a ſlave in a place, where ſhe ought to have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: and without having taſted any of the Sweets that others find in Marriage, to be expoſed to all the pains of without and within, that could attend ſo in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible a Union. She did nothing but ſhed Teares every day, but thoſe Teares inſtead of ſoftning the Heart of that Cruel <hi>Monarch,</hi> did but the more Irritate him; imagining that they were ſo many ſnares that the Goſſiping Humour of his Wife laid for his Honour.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs of <hi>Palomer,</hi> a Young Widdow, who was with the Queen in Quality of her Lady of Honour, extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touched to ſee ſo Charming a Princeſs treated after that manner, took ſo great a kindneſs for her, that there was no mannner of care, or Complaiſance which ſhe did not employ for the giving ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to her diſpleaſures, ſhe was a very lovely perſon of a good Wit, and of ſo engaging and ſweet a Humour, that it was a great Comfort to the ſad Queen, the having her with her, ſhe had loved her from the firſt day ſhe had ſeen her, and put in her an entire Confidence, imparting
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61828:18"/>to her all her troubles, to which the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs applyed, the ſofteſt remedies ſhe could imagine. But in fine the troubleſome Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the Old King; came to that point of Caprichiouſneſs and Impaſſion, that there was no longer bearing it, inſomuch that the Queen by the Council of her dear Counteſs, took the Reſolution of writing concerning it, to the King her Father, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that, as he had ever tenderly loved her, he would take pitty of the Condition, to which ſhe was reduced: and would take order at leaſt, that ſhe might be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better treated. But the diſſiculty was to find a faithfull and able Meſſenger, who would charge himſelf with the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and carry it to <hi>Naples.</hi> The Queen had not one Servant with her, in whom ſhe could truſt, they were ſo many ſpies that the King kept to take notice of all her acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: The Counteſs was obſerved as ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as ſhe, and the Kings cheif Miniſter was one, <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> from whoſe pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration and vigilance it was difficult to keep any thing of that Conſequence. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever at the length, ſeeing themſelves ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly perplexed, not knowing upon whom they ſhould caſt their Eyes for to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61828:19"/>ſerve them in this occaſion, without their deſign being in danger of coming to the King's knowledge, the Counteſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought her ſelf to propoſe to the Queen that ſame <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> the Kings cheif Miniſter. At which that Princeſs much ſurprized, asked her if ſhe rallyed, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the man of all the Kingdom, they ought moſt to fear, who was all the King's Council, and to whoſe perſuaſions ſhe fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied ſhe owed the greateſt part of the troubles ſhe ſuffered. It is true, Madam, anſwered the Counteſs, that <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> has a great power over the King's Spirit; that he is a Creature wholly devoted to him: and that perhaps to make his Court, he approves the Conduct, that is held with you. But it is likewiſe true, that this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter owes more to the <hi>Count de Palomer,</hi> whoſe charge he at preſent poſſeſſes, than to the King; that it was my deceaſed Husband, who made him what he is, and that he arrived not to that high degree of Fortune, not being of a Birth for that, but by his means. <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> Madam, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the Counteſs, whom the Queen liſtened to with Delight, is a <hi>Catalonian</hi> by Birth, and having the Reputation of a man
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61828:19"/>of great learning, it obliged the <hi>Count</hi> to ſend for him to <hi>Majorca,</hi> for to take care of the two Sons he had had by his firſt Wife. He was ſo ſatisfied with his Conduct, that after having employed him in ſome Affairs which he performed extreamly well, and like a man of ſence, he made him known to the King; advanced him from charge to charge, till that dying, he told the King, that there was not a man in his Kingdom who was more capable of that he poſſeſſed and which was going to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant by his Death, than <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> in which the King who beſides the eſteem he had, ever had of the Count's Penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, had a very great Opinion of <hi>Don Geronimo</hi>'s Capacity, followed my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Council, and as ſoon as he was dead, notwithſtanding all the Cabals at Court, for ſo Conſiderable a Charge, he advanced to it <hi>Don Geronimo.</hi> So much grace and ſo great an Obligation that he owed to the memory of his former Maſter, could not render a Man ungrateful, and I muſt needs ſay in his praiſe, that the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he has of it, is ſuch as I could deſire it; That he lives not with me as a cheif Miniſter of State, but as if he were ſtill
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61828:20"/>the <hi>Count's Domeſtick,</hi> with reſpects and cares that have never ceaſed, ſince my Husband's Death, intereſſing himſelf in all my Affairs as if they were his own, and I can likewiſe ſay that the Employ I have about you, Madam, is leſs an effect of the acknowledgment that the King owes to the good Services that the <hi>Count de Palomer</hi> has done him, than to the Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations of <hi>Don Geronimo.</hi> In fine, Madam, he has neglected nothing, not only of all that could be for my advantage, but of all that could pleaſe me, and what I have told you of the King, it is from him that I knew it; and all the Counſels that I have given you, came from him; thus, Madam, added the Counteſs, it is not to be feared but that if we employ him, he will ſerve us faithfully and uſefully. The Queen ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much Charmed to hear all theſe things, told her with an extream joy, that they needed not to go ſeek any farther, ſince they had for them the man of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who could the moſt eaſily and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger bring to paſs their deſign. Whereupon they concluded, that the Counteſs ſhould firſt ſpeak to him, to ſee if he were diſpoſed to ſerve the Queen in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61828:20"/>an Affair of that Conſequence, without telling him however what it was, and that the Queen ſhould afterwards finiſh the reſt. The Counteſs took her time one Morning that the King was gone a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, for the having the more Liberty, not only to diſcourſe him her ſelf, but to cauſe him to ſpeak to the Queen, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſent for him, he came immediately to her Chamber, where after a ſmall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging reveiw of all the cares he had for her, and having declared to him the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light ſhe took, to ſee how acknowledging he was, for what the <hi>Count de Palomer</hi> had done for him, ſhe fell to diſcourſe of the ſad Condition whereto the Poor Queen was reduced, which was the Subject, for which ſhe had ſent for him, not doubting but that he was ſenſible of it, eſteeming him as ſhe did, that he could do nothing to comfort her, and that nothing in the World could better declare him to be her Friend, than in endeavouring to find ſome means, that, that lovely Princeſs might be treated with leſs Cruelty, aſſuring him that ſhe was ſo ſenſibly touched at her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Deſtiny: that ſhe ſuffered more than the half of her pains. <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:61828:21"/>the moſt Ardent of all men in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the obliging the Counteſs, after having aſſured her, that he had neither Goods, Fortune, nor Life, which ſhe might not diſpoſe of, and which he would not employ for her, and for all that ſhe loved, declared to her, that he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready impatient to know what the Queen deſired of him; Whereupon the Counteſs made him paſs into that Princeſs's Cabinet, where ſhe expected him, for the having a more ſecret Conference with him; As ſhe had prepared her ſelf for what ſhe was to tell him, and that ſhe knew that the Connteſs had made the advances that were neceſſary, ſhe no ſooner ſaw him in her Cabinet, out of which the Counteſs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, for fear ſome Body ſhould hear them, than that falling to the buſineſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, ſhe told him, that being at length wearied with the Viſions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Caprichio's of the King, not to ſay follies and rage: That ſhe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to write of it to the King her Father, and that ſhe prayed him if he had any Conſideration, or at leaſt any pitty of an unfortunate Princeſs, he would furniſh her with the means for the doing this;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61828:21"/>and aid her with his Councel and Credit, to procure ſome Temperament to the ſad State of her Life, and that the King her Husband might Treat her with a little more ſoftneſs. <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> who had hearkened to all this diſcourſe, with the poſture of a Man who was profoundly applyed, to the Propoſition that was made him; was ſometime without anſwering the Queen, for the making appear of what importance that was ſhe deſired of him. After which he repreſented to her, the difficulties there was in this deſign, into what incidents he might Precipitate himſelf, if he ſo far proceeded to ſerve her, wherein not only his Fortune was concerned, which he would not conſider, in the Honour and Joy he ſhould have of contributing any thing to the eaſing her pains; but his Life, if the King got the leaſt knowledge of it, and that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded ſome time to think of it. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he prayed her to give him at leaſt the reſt of the day for that end, the Queen granted it him, but ſhe preſently fancied, that it was a Pretexte, that ſhe had conſided in a man, who only deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded time to conſider of it, that he might
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61828:22"/>excuſe himſelf the more Civilly. <hi>Don Geronims</hi> being retired, the Counteſs entred the Cabinet, where ſhe ſaw the Queen with a ſad air, which preſaged to her nothing of happy for their Enterprize. Has <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> Madam, deceived my hopes? Not quite, anſwered ſhe, but the pain he is in, among ſo many dangers he ſees, to employ himſelf for us, makes me fear he will not charge himſelf with this Affair: After which relating to her the reſt of the Conference they had had to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſhe made her ſee how little they were to rely on his Succours: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Counteſs, who would not beleive that ſhe had vainly ſlattered her ſelf of the Credit ſhe fancied ſhe had with this Miniſter, begg'd the Queen not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, till that ſhe had ſpoke to him once more; and that very Evening ſhe ſent for him, thinking her ſelf too much concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, after the advances ſhe had made, not to make uſe of all ſhe thought moſt effective to engage him not to refuſe. <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> came, who knowing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was called, Compoſed his Face ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deſign, and appeared at firſt with the Air of a Man ſo Melancholly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61828:22"/>and ſo perplexed, that the Counteſs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt loſt her hopes of reducing him to what ſhe deſired. Hereupon ſhe renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her preſſing ways and full of Charmes, to endeavour to put him in a better Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: The Cunning <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtill difficult, he told her into how many dangers ſuch an Affair was capable of drawing a Man, and ſhowed her yet greater diſſiculties than to the Queen; But the Counteſs not willing to ſtop in ſo fair a way, and perceiving notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that this Miniſter told her, that ſhe might yet gain him; asked him what was become of thoſe Proteſtations ſo oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en reiterated, that he had neither Fortune nor Life that ſhe might not diſpoſe of, and puſhing that point ſtill farther in telling him that the ſhame of this refuſal would fall all upon her, becauſe it was ſhe who had engaged the Queen to declare her ſelf to him, from whom ſhe had promiſed her ſelf more zeal to oblige her, than he made appear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there is no manner of ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, looks, ſentiments, aſſurances of friendſhip, and all that a pretty Woman has of moſt engageing to bring a Man to her will, but what ſhe employed, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61828:23"/>ſeeing that this Miniſter begun to yeild, ſhe was in a greater joy than ſhe could make appear. The ſenſible <hi>Don Geroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> who was touched to the very bottom of his Heart, by all the Counteſs ſaid, ſuffering himſelf to be carried away with the motions that Tranſported him, took one of her fair hands, which he dared to kiſs. That action made the Lady ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing bluſh, having ever ſeen <hi>Don Gero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo</hi> with the greateſt reſpect for her: but the conjuncture of time and the need they had of him, would have procured his Pardon for much greater Liberty. She could have deſired he would have gon to the Queens apartment, to impart to her himſelf the good intentions he had for her ſervice; but he excuſed himſelf upon ſome preſſing Affair, which demanded his atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the King; and prayed her at the ſame time that ſhe would her ſelf carry the news, that he was ready to riſque all for her ſake, as he would not fail to go and confirm to her the next day at her ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Counteſs ſaw him gone, ſhe run immediately to the Queen to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint her with <hi>Don Geronimo</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61828:23"/>which was really to her the moſt agreable news ſhe could have brought; but which required the aſſurances of the Miniſter himſelf to be in perfect joy, of which he did not fail at the Hour he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and he charged himſelf not only with the Letter ſhe would write to the King her Father; but to make it have the ſucceſs ſhe deſired, to accompany it with one of his own, which ſhould be no leſs effectual: the Queen willing to ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledge his zeal, told him that he would all his Life find, not only a Prop in her, whoſe power was not great in <hi>Major<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> but a Protector in the Perſon of the King of <hi>Naples,</hi> who could better acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg than ſhe the Service he rendred her. <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> liſtening to what the Queen told him, with an air indifferent enough, the King your Father, Madam, anſwered he is a great <hi>Monaoch,</hi> and can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the Ambition of a Man much more Elevated by Fortune than I am, but it is not what I ſeek, Madam, and you can do more here for me than I can deſire, for the being the moſt happy of all men, I know not, continued he ſiighing, if the reſpect I owe to your Majeſty, ſhould
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61828:24"/>permit me to purſue this diſcourſe, but I fancied, that in abandoning my Life for you, you would if you could, render it happy. He ſtopped here ſome moments without ſaying any thing, during which the Queen was in great pain, fearing that in the diſorder ſhe ſaw him, he would make uſe of the neceſſity there was of him, for the exacting ſomething from her that might be contrary to her Glory: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſhe was two or three times upon the point of ſending him back, without hearing him any more. When <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> taking Courage, I know, Madam, purſued he, that it is not for ſuch a man as I, to dare to make his Queen his confident, and ſuch a Queen as your Majeſty; but I can only addreſs my ſelf to you, and the Paſſion I have for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Palomer,</hi> being ſuch that I can no longer conceal it, I have hopes that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on you to render any one of the Court happy, you will conſider the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of a man who is willing to ſacrifice himſelf for the endeavouring to render you leſs unfortunate. This Princeſs who did really tremble, and changed Colour twice or thrice, was raviſhed with joy,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61828:24"/>that this ſigh was not addreſſed to her, ſo that ſhe eaſily pardoned him the Liberty of his Confidence; and not being able to hold from laughing at the fear ſhe had, ſhe asked him, if the Counteſs knew the ſentiments, he had for her: upon which this Lover anſwering, that reſpect had ever hindred him from declaring them to her, although he had been more than Six Years paſſionately in Love, ſhe took upon her to acquaint her with them, and to ſerve him as much as ſhe could. This ſo overjoyed the Amourous <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> that caſting himſelf at her Feet, he could not be thankfull enough for ſo much good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The Queen made him riſe, and told him, that he might repoſe in her the intereſts of his Heart, and that he ſhould think of her Letter Affair which this Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver promiſed her, and went to labour that moment for the diſpatching away ſecretly for <hi>Naples,</hi> a <hi>Brigantine</hi> of Twelve Oars of a ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> being retired, and the Countess coming to the Queen, was much ſurprized to find her laughing all alone, ſhe made known to her the joy ſhe had to ſee her in ſo good a Humour, and begged
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61828:25"/>ſhe would impart to her with the ſooneſt the Subject of it, that ſhe might alſo laugh; this Princeſs told her, that ſhe charged her ſelf with a Commiſſion to her, which ſhe knew not if ſhe ſhould come of with Honour: but that it was ſo extraordinary, that though it was upon a very ſerious matter, ſhe could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſhe ſhould acquit her ſelf of it in that Tone, and that in a word, if there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened any change in her misfortunes, ſhe ſhould be obliged for it to her Charmes, for the Love of which the paſſionate <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> was obliged to ſerve her. The Counteſs bluſhed at the Queens Raillery, remembring the boldneſs he had for to kiſs her Hand, which had then made her ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſomething; but ſhe fell a laughing with the Princeſs and told her, that ſhe had well foreſeen that ſhe ſhould pay all the charges of that Embaſſy; that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſhe ſhould never have beleived, that the Folly of a man of that Birth, who had been her Domeſtick: could have mounted to have conſidered her upon that Foot, and that now ſhe ſaw that Fortune made People Blind. The Queen took the Lovers part, and the thing having been
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61828:25"/>again turned into Raillery, ſhe told her the fear ſhe had been in her ſelf: and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of her at the ſame time ſhe would ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the Spirit of this man, till that her buſineſs was done, which the Counteſs the more caſily promiſed her, for that ſhe prepared to divert her ſelf with the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Miniſter, as well as make uſe of it for the obtaining what they deſired of him.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> had at that time, an Army before <hi>Catenzano,</hi> under the Command of the <hi>Count d' Artois,</hi> who beſeiged it by Sea and Land. Which King <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon</hi> having learnt he departed from <hi>Sicily</hi> with a powerful Fleet, for the releiveing that City with Five Hundred men at Armes, and <hi>de Loria</hi> his Admiral; but he found thoſe of <hi>Charles,</hi> with the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorquins</hi> in ſo good order before the Port of <hi>Catenzano,</hi> that he never durſt attack them, nor attempt the Succours on that ſide. He fancied it would be more eaſie for him by Land: Wherefore having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embarqued his <hi>Catalonians,</hi> with <hi>de Loria,</hi> they advanced towards the Army of the <hi>Count d' Artois,</hi> who repulſed them as far as the Sea, conſtraining them to get with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61828:26"/>all haſte into their Galleys. Which was the only time that that great Captain <hi>Roger de Loria</hi> was ever Conquered, <hi>Charles</hi> the Second received the Letter of the Queen of <hi>Majorca,</hi> his Daughter at the ſame time he did the news of this Vict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory; and the one raiſing in him as much pitty as the other gave him joy, he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſend expreſly an Ambaſſador to the King of <hi>Majorca,</hi> to make him his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints. He made choice for that Embaſſy of <hi>Count Hannibal d' Aveline,</hi> as one who had not only the moſt Wit and Merit of any Lord of the Court, but was moſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of performing his Commiſſion; and ſpeaking with the requiſite Tone to the King of <hi>Majorca.</hi> Wherefore he bid him prepare himſelf with the ſooneſt for this Voyage, and gave order at the ſame time, for the making ready Three Galleys, for the carrying him with all his Train, to the Iſle of <hi>Majorca.</hi> He wrote Three Letters, one for this King, the other for the Queen, and the Third for <hi>Don Gero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo,</hi> which <hi>Count Hannibal</hi> had orders to deliver him in particular, and to teſtify to him how ſenſible the King was of the good Offices, he rendred to the Queen his Daughter.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:61828:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Hannibal</hi> was not ſo much Charmed with the Honour of this employ; becauſe that the King thereby diſtinguiſhed him from ſo many other Lords in that Court, as, becauſe it gave him the opportunity of rendring an important ſervice to a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, he had ſo paſſionately loved, and theſe hopes renewing a flame in his Heart, that neither abſence nor any other reaſon had been yet able to extinguiſh, he uſed all manner of cares, diligence, meaſures, and precaution that his Deputation might ſucceed to the advantage and contentment of the Queen. Her Beauty returned into his mind with more force than ever, and more in Love than he had ever been with her Charmes; all that he ſaid and did, ſince the King had given him this Commiſſion, was only for his fair Princeſs, till his arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val at <hi>Majorca,</hi> which was at ſix of the Clock in the Morning, with Three of the fineſt Galleys of <hi>Naples,</hi> having brought with him a Hundred Young Gentlemen, whom his merit as well as his magnificence and Liberality bound to his Perſon: He landed with this fine Train, which imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately drew all the People to ſee them diſembarke, and they were ſo aſtoniſhed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61828:27"/>at the richneſs of the habits as well as the good meen of the cheif and of thoſe of his Company, that the report run immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the City, that it was King <hi>Charles</hi> himſelf who came to ſee his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This news being preſently carryed to <hi>Belver,</hi> came to the Ears of the King of <hi>Majorca,</hi> who, not knowing what to think of it, ſent inceſſantly <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> to inform himſelf of the truth. The Queen, who had heard the report, as ſoon as the King, had an unſpeakable joy: and having ſent for the Counteſs of <hi>Palo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> they went together into her Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, from whence they ſaw thoſe Three Galleys. For <hi>Belver</hi> is upon a riſing ground, which commands over all the City. They were in ſuch delight, that their joy was heard by all the apartment. They were however in great pain as well as the King, to know who was come, not doubting but that it was ſome one that the King of <hi>Naples</hi> had ſent in Conſequence of their Letter, and they expected with great impatience, as well as the King, the return of <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> to give them certain News: In the mean time they did
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61828:27"/>not fail to Figure to themſelves a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand things thereupon.</p>
            <p>This Miniſter being arrived at the City, in the time, that <hi>Count Hannibal</hi> was juſt landed, and having conducted him to the <hi>Town-Hall,</hi> through ſuch a crowd of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they could hardly paſs through the Streets, he had, after ſome Ceremonies of Civility, a particular diſcourſe with him. The <hi>Count</hi> gave him the Letter that the King wrote to him, which he opened, and read the particular Teſtimonies that that <hi>Monarch</hi> gave him of his eſteem and favour. From thence paſſing to the Affair in hand, <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> gave to the <hi>Count</hi> the neceſſary inſtructions upon the meaſures he was to take, and the manner he was to conduct himſelf, after which they both mounted into one of the Kings Litters, to go to <hi>Belver,</hi> whether <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> had already ſent a Gentleman to give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to the King of the arrival of this Ambaſſador<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This Prince received him with the moſt Curtezy and Honour, that his Humour, little proper for theſe publick Ceremonies, could permit him. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview was very rare that was made in this Reception; where the King on one
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61828:28"/>part dreſſed like a dull heavy Merchant, accompanied with Ten or Twelve Lords of his Court, who had no better meens, nor were better apparelled than himſelf, and on the other <hi>Count Hannibal,</hi> who was the handſomeſt Youth of all <hi>Italy,</hi> all ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with Gold and the Jewels he had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, with that great number of Gentlemen, all extreamly well dreſſed, with a Courtly Air, which Charmed, and at the ſame time aſtoniſhed all thoſe <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorquins.</hi> They made a noiſe in entring the Place, and eſpecially the <hi>French,</hi> who made the greateſt number, that one would have ſaid they went to beſeige this poor King; <hi>Count Hannibal</hi> after having made his Conge in the Chamber of Audience, where he expected him; ſpoak to him with a Grace and an Eloquence, that the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe Soul of this <hi>Monarch</hi> was Charmed with the praiſes that he gave him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came good natur'd in favour of him, and more mild; he embraced him Two or Three times with marks of kindneſs he had never ſhown to any one, ſo much power over the moſt obdurate Hearts, has a Perſon whom Nature has took delight in accompliſhing.</p>
            <p>The firſt audience, which was about Ten of the Clock in the Morning, being
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61828:28"/>paſſed in Compliments and Ceremonies; there was a particular one about Eight a Clock in the Evening, in which the <hi>Count</hi> declared to the King the Subject of his Embaſſy, in delivering him the Letter that the King his Maſter wrote to him; and by which he prayed him to conſider that the Princeſs he had marryed, was the Daughter of a <hi>Monarch,</hi> not fit to be treated after the manner he did, that thoſe were not the conditions of their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance. That he very well know, that he had promiſed him to have that regard for her that was due to Daughters of her Rank: That ſhe ſhould live at <hi>Majorca,</hi> as ſhe had lived at <hi>Naples,</hi> and that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the difference was ſo great, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving deprived her, upon her arriving at his Court, of all the Domeſticks he had himſelf given her, he had learnt from good hands, that ſhe had hardly People capable of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her, and that ſhe was kept ſhut up in her apartment, as a Criminal of State, or as if ſhe were accuſed of ſome infamous crime; that this belonged more to a ſlave than a Queen, that he prayed him, not as a King; but as his Ally, Friend and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-Law, that he would change his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61828:29"/>conduct, and treat his Daughter after a manner that all the Earth might not reproach him, with having ſo ill marryed a Princeſs, who merited, and who could have had a more happy Deſtiny, than that of being his Wife.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Majorca</hi> well ſaw, that King <hi>Charles</hi> his Father-in-Law wrote to him, as a Prince, who had newly got a Famous Victory: and who begun to have no more need of him. He was of a more peaceable than Warlike Humour: and not being willing to draw upon himſelf the enmity of ſo powerful a <hi>Monarch,</hi> he endeavoured to excuſe upon the cuſtom of the Country, the conduct he had thitherto held with the Queen; but that, ſince it did not pleaſe the King his Father-in Law, he would to diſabuſe him of the falſe Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that might have been made him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate himſelf as he ſhould judge moſt convenient. And it was concluded, that very moment, with <hi>Count Hannibal,</hi> that the Queen ſhould enjoy a modeſt Liberty, for to walk when ſhe pleaſed within and without the Palace of <hi>Belver,</hi> when ſhe thought fit: that of the Perſons who ſhould ſerve her, ſhe might chooſe Six, over whom ſhe ſhould have an entire pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61828:29"/>and that in fine the People who would ſee her, or who had Affairs with her, might approach her without any difficulty. All thoſe Articles of Peace being thus concluded, the King would out of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Civility; that the <hi>Count</hi> himſelf ſhould carry the news of it to the Queen, whom he had not yet ſeen, and prayed him at the ſame time he would make his Peace with her. <hi>Hannibal</hi> promiſed him what he deſired: and going to her apartment, where ſhe expected him with the Counteſs of <hi>Palomer,</hi> he ſaluted her, but with a joy, and ſuch motions of Love, fear and reſpect, that are difficult to be deſcribed: and I beleive that it is all that a very paſſionate man can do to imagine them. The diſcontent of that Princeſs, had not at all leſſened her Beauty; on the contrary they had added a certain lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, which in the midſt of ſo many Charmes, had the moſt engaging effect imaginable. The amorous Ambaſſador loſt at that ſight all his ſenſes to his very Speech; and had occaſion for all the force of his Courage to uphold himſelf, his Countenance changed Colour Two or Three times, and not daring hardly to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61828:30"/>look again upon the Queen, ſince the firſt time he had ſeen her, he remained as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, and without ſaying any thing, in ſo great a ſpace of time, that that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs knowing that no man had more wit than he, was much ſurprized at it. She had no Body near her but the Counteſs, and <hi>Hannibal</hi> was likewiſe alone, all the People of their Trains being retired on both ſides out of reſpect. Inſomuch that the Queen not ſeeing what could hinder the <hi>Count</hi> from making known to her what he had to ſay, in ſo fine a Subject for the ſhowing his wit, was as much concerned as he, at the perplexities in which ſhe ſaw him; and beginning to ſpeak that he might recover himſelf, ſhe told him, that ſhe was extreamly obliged to the King her Father, not only for the affection he ſhewed her in ſuch an occaſion, but for that he had given this Commiſſion to the man of all his Kingdom, ſhe ſhould have deſired to have had it, if it had depended on her choice. This Princeſs good and generous as ſhe was, beleived, that ſhe ought at leaſt to acknowledge with words as obliging as thoſe were, the Service that the <hi>Count</hi> had juſt done her: beſides that,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61828:30"/>what ſhe told him was perfectly according to her ſentiments: but this Lover, who was Charmed enough with the pleaſure of ſeeing her, without her needing to add out of ſo extraordinary a goodneſs fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours which quite confounded him with Love, was upon the point of falling upon his knees, if ſhe had not hindred him. It is a little too much, My Lord, ſaid ſhe to him ſmiling; and that Exceſs of Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion would not become a man of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter you have here. I can never render you enough, Madam, replyed the <hi>Count,</hi> who began to come to himſelf, all your due, for there is nothing ſubmiſſive enough which belongs not to you. It is true, continued he, that I am ſent hither as an Ambaſſador from the King of <hi>Naples,</hi> but it is when I am before the King of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorca,</hi> and before you, Madam, I am but your Subject, a Title much more glorious for me, than all thoſe that the greateſt Kings of the Earth can give me, and which does not diſpenſe me from any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect near you. But after what manner ſoever you ſhould conſider me, Madam, added he, whether as the Ambaſſador of the King your Father, or as your Subject,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61828:31"/>you may order me all that you pleaſe; for I am ſent only to this Court to obey you, and to have what rendred to you, that is your due. The King of <hi>Majorca</hi> is going to change his conduct in what concernes you, or at leaſt he has promiſed me to do it: That if he fails in it, and that with all the Honour and reſpect they owe you, he gives you not the Liberty you deſire, I have order to tell him, that you belong to a <hi>Monarch</hi> extreamly jealous of his Glory: and whoſe reſentment for the injury ſhall be done you, will proceed much farther, than if it were done to his own perſon. He ſtill enlarged more at length upon the particular orders he had received from the King; and which concerned the Queen, but with terms ſo ſtrong and paſſionate, that ſhe was extreamly touched with ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, and could not hinder her ſelf from ſhowing it him by a Thouſand goodneſſes, of which the moſt important for the amorous <hi>Hannibal,</hi> was that of her picture, which ſhe gave him. Never Lover loaded with Honour and Grace, felt ſo much joy as the <hi>Count</hi> did at that preſent. The leaſt favour from the Hand of that Charming Princeſs, would have
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61828:31"/>been more conſiderable to him than all the Riches of the World: and it is credible, that that of a Picture, for which he would have given a Thouſand Lives, was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing very Charming to him.</p>
            <p>The Queen paſſing to the News that ſhe would know of the Court of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the <hi>Count</hi> having ſatisfied her in all that ſhe deſired, ſhe beleived, it was not yet conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to lay hold of the new Articles of Peace, between her and the King; and made it a ſmall Subject of raillery with the <hi>Count;</hi> after which this Lover taking leave of the Queen retired to his apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where he paſſed the moſt pleaſant Hours that a happy Lover had ever had.</p>
            <p>The Queen, ſince her being in that Court, having ſeen none but ſuch People as raiſed her pity, and having had an eſteem of a long time for the <hi>Count,</hi> could not hinder her ſelf in ſeeing him from ſhowing the joy ſhe had of his arrival, and even to ſeel ſomething more ſtrong, that thoſe motions finding him better made, as ſeem'd to her, than ſhe had ever ſeen him; and afterwards paſſing over in her mind part of the things, he had told
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:61828:32"/>her, ſhe found in his air and manner of expreſſion, ſomething ſo Witty and ſo Gallant that ſhe ſigh'd, in making reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on all ſhe had quitted. The truth is, the <hi>Count</hi> had a great part in that ſigh, but the Hour was not yet come, that this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery which did but appear in her ſhould be diſcovered: Her Heart which ſhe had ſince that Evening ſilled with a Thouſand different things, cauſed her deſires to floate diverſly, ſometimes upon one Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, ſometimes upon another: but that which moſt poſſeſſed her, was the ſilence and the diſorder into which the <hi>Count</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately fell in ſeeing her, and this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by certain looks and a paſſionate action, that ſhe had obſerved in him; and which exceeded the ardour of an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Subject, ſeemed to learn her a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, of which ſhe had had formerly a great deal of Suſpicion. In the favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able diſpoſition ſhe then was, this thought muſts needs give her at firſt a great deal of pleaſure, but certain returns on the ſide of Glory; coming to deſtroy in one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment all theſe Amorous Fancies, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached her ſelf with the very weakneſs of thinking of them. In the mean time
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61828:32"/>notwithſtanding, all theſe glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, the mind taking the party of the Heart, as it uſually happens, ſhe fell into it inceſſantly, and paſſed one part of the Night in diſquiets. Not that ſhe diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf, and that ſhe did not beleive ſhe had Empire enough over her Heart, to hinder, from entring therein any thing that might be called paſſion; but it was, that ſhe feared, that the eſteem, perhaps a little too great, that ſhe had for a Gentleman ſo well made and ſo dangerous, might not inſenſibly engage her to treat him more favourably than ſhe ought, if it was true, what ſhe imagined, that he had Sentiments ſo little reſpectuous for her, and that this might not give him at the ſame time an occaſion of flattering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And in this thought ſhe did, all that ſhe could, to irritate her ſelf againſt him; but ſhe found ſo little reaſon to do it, that that even betrayed her, and engaged her whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe would or no to juſtify him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Count</hi> paſſed the Night much more agreeably. He had a long time made it his happineſs to love that Charming Princeſs without telling it her, and without hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61828:33"/>any thing; and then <hi>Swimming</hi> in a ſort of languiſhing full of joy, he repreſented to himſelf with what Grace ſhe had received, with what kindneſs and goodneſs ſhe had ſpoke to him; but above all that Divine Picture ſhe had given him in ſo obliging a manner, and which he inceſſantly kiſſed, as being the Crown of his happineſs, the Night laſted but little in that manner, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he paſſed it without ſleeping; and <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> who had not yet made him a viſit, coming to ſee him in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was received by him with that kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that was recommended to him by King <hi>Charles</hi> his Maſter, and which the ſervices merited he had rendred to the Queen his Daughter, and the truth is, the Ambaſſadors Soul was then ſo ſatisfied, that he would have been pleaſing to his very Ennemies; They then contracted a very great Friendſhip, and as thoſe of Court are uſually founded upon ſome inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, that of Love was principally what engaged them: the <hi>Count</hi> becauſe that he ſaw, that the Friendſhip of a Man as <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> who governed the Old King's mind, could not but be uſeful to him; and the other, becauſe that he judged,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61828:33"/>that it would be to make his Court to the Queen, the being united in Friendſhip with the Ambaſſador, and to have at the ſame time a pretexte of the oftner ſeeing the Counteſs. There was preſently the beſt underſtanding between them poſſible, they were almoſt ever ſeen together, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when they were to go to the Queen; which the <hi>Count</hi> affected for the giving the leſs Ombrage to the King, with whom <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> made it likewiſe a merit, that he ever accompanied the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador in theſe occaſions, rendring after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an account of what paſſed in thoſe viſits, ſuch as he judged convenient, for the entertaining him in the confidence he had of him. But at the length this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of State, who was a clear ſighted man, remarquing a great Change in the Counteſs's mind, as well as in her manner of treating him; and that the Society he had made with that Ambaſſador, had been more diſadvantageous than uſeful to him, eſpecially ſince ſome daies, that the Queen, more retired, ſhowed her ſelf leſs than uſually, the Counteſs then paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing whole Afternoons in entertaining her ſelf with the <hi>Count,</hi> without daigning
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61828:34"/>once to caſt her Eyes upon him. <hi>Don Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronimo,</hi> I ſay, vexed to the very bottom of his Soul, to be thus treated, and weary with acting the part he did, reſolved to Troop a part and render his viſits in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, for to ſee if it was out of modeſty before that Ambaſſador, or becauſe there was no more occaſion for him, that he was looked upon with that indifference. He feared that they had really changed their Sentiments for him, and that he had been the Inſtrument of his own misfortune: but the thing required ſome light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came to Complaints; and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign was not difficult to be Executed. He took the pretexte of an Affair of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as it happened to him often enough to pray the <hi>Count</hi> to excuſe him, if he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not accompany him that day to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Queens; His excuſe was very kindly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, for that Ambaſſador who had alſo his reaſons to quit his Company, was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pain to find the means to be civilly rid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> him. The Counteſs of <hi>Palomer,</hi> whom h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſidered as the Queens Heart and Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell, and of whom he had demanded the reaſon why that Princeſs was become ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſolitary, ſince ſome days that ſhe could no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:61828:34"/>be ſeen, had told him, that <hi>Don Geroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> was the cauſe; but the truth was, that it was ſhe that was weary of him, and who would have been glad to have enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the <hi>Count</hi> without ſuch a Witneſs, who obſerved her leaſt actions. In the mean time the Ambaſſador was extreamly concerned he had no ſooner known what the Counteſs told him; gave her many thanks for her advice, and promiſed her to make uſe of it. But what the Queen feared, was not the ſight of <hi>Don Geroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> the Counteſs had ſpoke for her: and that Princeſs on the contrary very much approved therein the <hi>Count</hi>'s Conduct. What ſhe ſhun'd and rendred her ſolitary, was the ſight of that Lover: But retreat and ſolitude are ill remedies againſt Love. The violence ſhe uſed upon her ſelf that ſhe might not go and ſee him when ſhe knew he was in her Antichamber with the Counteſs, more augmented her ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour than a diſcourſe of ſeveral Hours. In ſine ſhe knew not what to do, nor what to ſay, and ſhe ſaw that her Heart became dayly more weak againſt ſo Charming a Paſſion: if any thing was capable of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying it, it was what the Counteſs told
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61828:35"/>her, at the return from the diſcourſes ſhe had had with the <hi>Count;</hi> for the Queen ever very paſſionate and very curious to know what he had ſaid to her, did not fail to ſend for her as ſoon as that Lover had quitted her, and to demand upon what he had entertained her. The Counteſs, who conſidered this Ambaſſador as a Conqueſt already made, needed not to be much preſſed, to brag of it to the Queen, and with the air of a Woman ſomething vain, and who would make her ſelf beleived ſhe told that Princeſs, that his diſcourſe was alwaies of Gallantry, attended with ſighs and paſſionate looks, which eſcaped from the <hi>Count,</hi> who was ever commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Beauty. The Queen told her, to undeceive her, that all this was very uſua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the Court of <hi>Naples,</hi> where all the Young Lords thought it the Devoir of a Gallant man, when they were with any Lady to ſay to her kind things, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was very dangerous to truſt in them The truth is, that the <hi>Count,</hi> judging tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Counteſs's Friendſhip, who had all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Power with the Queen, was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luetly neceſſary to him, had neglected no thing that might get him into her favour
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61828:35"/>and that, as he was extreamly amorous, Courtſhip and kindneſs coſt him nothing, and he had been more perſuaſive to that Lady than he deſired: becauſe that ſhe would really be perſuaded that he loved her. In the mean time the Queen, whom ſhe had Twice or Thrice acquainted with the ſame thing, not knowing what to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive of it, and inceſſantly attacqued with a Thouſand different thoughts, reſolved to have an Eclairciſsment, there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more capable of curing her of that paſſion, than the truth, of what the Counteſs told her. She was thus diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when her Lady of Honour came to tell her, that <hi>Count Hannibal</hi> asked to ſpeak with her. It was what ſhe deſired, however notwithſtanding, the Reſolution that ſhe had taken, ſhe ballanced, and would not have yet been ſtrong enough to have Executed her deſign, if the deſire ſhe had to ſee him, had not made way for her to reſolve of it. Whereof ſhe bid the Counteſs bring him in. I come, Madam, ſaid the <hi>Count</hi> as he entred, to ask you a Thouſand Pardons for my imprudence, in not having judged, that it was too great a Grace you did in granting me the Honour
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:61828:36"/>of ſeeing you ſometimes, without charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf with the Company of a man as <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> who might be to you in the end troubleſom and incommode. I know not, anſwered the Queen very much aſtoniſhed at this diſcourſe, who has ſo ill informed you of my Sentiments; but far from having diſapproved your Conduct therein, I found it very reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> added ſhe, is a man to whom I have Obligations, I cannot enough acknowledge, I am acquainted with his merit and probity. And he ſhall not only be kindly received when he comes in your Company; but I declare to you, that I ſhall never more willingly ſee you, than when he is with you. <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> Madam, replyed the <hi>Count,</hi> is much more happy than I imagined, and I ſhall for the future better know how to judge of the Sentiments you have for Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, than to attribute to them the cauſe of the unhappineſs, which deprives me of the Honour of ſeeing you, without which I ſhould have nothing more to do here. Let us let <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> alone, replyed the Queen, not being willing to enter into this diſcourſe; and tell me from whence
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61828:36"/>it proceeds, that having related to me the particular Affairs of the Court of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the adventures of ſeveral Lords, you have told me nothing of your own. Do you keep them for the Laſt? Or do you beleive that there is too much vanity to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint with them your ſelf, without that I deſire it. I beleive Madam, anſwered the <hi>Count,</hi> I have forgot nothing of all the Gallantry that paſſed in that Court, ſince your leaving it, for as to what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes me, I can aſſure, that there has been nothing in all that time which merits your Curioſity; and that in all my Life, I never paſſed my time with ſo much trouble and ill Humour. How is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, replyed the Queen, that that amou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Star which rules over that Court ſhould have no Influence upon you. This is ſo true, Madam, replyed the <hi>Caunt,</hi> that what inclination ſoever I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had for pleaſures, I was never ſeen at them but when an indiſpenſible devoir called me to them, or when the Service of the King my Maſter was concerned, or that I was to give him an account of the orders he had been pleaſed to give me; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in thoſe Caſes I was ever at my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61828:37"/>Houſe, it being moſt ſuitable to the Humour I then was in, and where I had reſolved to paſs the reſt of Life. The Change is great, ſaid the Quen to him; who eaſily comprehended that that ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Life regarded her, and we ſhould not be much in pain to be perſuaded, that it is the effect of ſome unhappy Deſtiny; But however, if People are to be beleived who obſerve you, you have not the air of an indifferent man, and whether it is that you have found more Charmes in this Court, than in that of <hi>Naples,</hi> you are not ſeen to ſeek Solitude ſo much. The <hi>Count,</hi> bluſhing at theſe words, could not hinder ſighing, which being preſently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Queen, you ſigh, my Lord, ſaid ſhe, Ah! you are in Love, and you ſhall acquaint me with the Cauſe of that ſigh, or I ſhall be no longer your Friend. If I have any favour to demand of you, Madam, anſwered the <hi>Count</hi> with a trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and paſſionate voice, it is, not to oblige me to tell you a thing, that I ſhould rather dye than declare to whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it was. This Charming Princeſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a greater fear than he, that he ſhould explain himſelf too clearly, was not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61828:37"/>willing to preſs him any more: However as ſhe was in pain to quit ſo ſoon, a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which ſo much pleaſed her, ſhe could not ſtop there, and reviewing him with an air to force the ſecret from a Heart: but in fine, ſaid ſhe to him, you will at leaſt confeſs to me, that this ſad and penſive Humour has not alwaies laſted in you, and that whether at <hi>Naples,</hi> or in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, you are in Love. It is true, I Love, Divine Princeſs, anſwered that Lover all Tranſported, and with the moſt extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary paſſion that ever one has loved. I have been in Love purſued he ſighing, theſe Five Years, that is to ſay, from the moment I could know what Love was, and I have from that time felt all that can be imagined of moſt tender and ardent in a Heart: and at the ſame time all that there is of moſt ſubmiſſive and fulleſt of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in devoir. All this, Madam, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out daring to tell it, and without hopes. The Queen, fearing that ſhe could not anſwer this diſcourſe without its coſting her ſome weakneſs, conſidering the looks and paſſionate action with which that Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver accompanyed it, would rid her ſelf of it; and riſing from whence ſhe was, I
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:61828:38"/>pitty you, ſaid ſhe, and went at the ſame time into a <hi>Balcony</hi> there was to her Chamber, for to hide the diſorder, into which a Thouſand different motions caſt her which roſe in her Soul. The <hi>Count</hi> followed to the <hi>Balcony</hi> Door, where ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, he ſaw ſhe ſaid nothing more, and that ſhe did not ſo much as look upon him. Wherefore after having beeen ſome time in that Poſture and ſilence, he thought it was his duty to retire. But the Queen turning then towards him; What do you go away, ſaid ſhe to him, without having ſatisfied me upon what I deſire: and ſhall I not know who that Beauty is for whom you have ſo long ſighed. I have told you, Madam, anſwered that Lover, with a very ſubmiſſive voice, that it would be leſs trouble to me to take away my Life, than this ſecret. And the only Grace I demand of you is to let it dye with me. You put but little confidence in People, replyed the Queen, and to let you ſee, I have more conſideration for you, I not only conſent you tell me nothing of it, but I even forbid it you: and paſſing at the ſame time from the <hi>Balcony</hi> into her Cabinet, ſhe left
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61828:38"/>the <hi>Count</hi> in a terrible fright.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> was then with the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs. This Miniſter being deſirous to know his Deſtiny with that Lady, came alone to the Queens Antichamber, where he found her Penſive, but ſo profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ſhe hardly ſaw him enter. He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached her: and notwithſtanding all he could ſay, he ſaw, ſhe could hardly open her Mouth to make him an anſwer. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that taking from thence an occaſion of explaining himſelf, he told her, that he knew not if he had been unhappy enough to diſpleaſe her in any thing; but that he had obſerved that of late, ſhe had much diminiſhed the eſteem ſhe had formerly had for him; and that ſhe would oblige him extreamly, and likewiſe draw him out of a very great pain, if ſhe would be ſo kind as to acquaint him with the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it. The Counteſs, who imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately comprehended whither theſe Complaints tended, and not being willing to give this Miniſter a reaſon for them, knowing his dangerous Spirit, ſhe anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him very obligingly, that as thitherto ſhe had had all manner of reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61828:39"/>him, ſhe had likewiſe for him the ſame conſideration ſhe had ever had, but that ſince ſome time, ſhe had taken, but ſhe could not tell at what, a certain ſad and Melancholly Humour, which made ſeveral People complain of her as well as he, and that they who knew her ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pitty than blame her. <hi>Don Gero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo</hi> was not ſatisfied with this excuſe: He knew, from whence her diſeaſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, or at leaſt he very much ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected it; However without ſeeming to know any thing; he told her that Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement was the only remedy for ſuch ſort of ills; and propoſed to her at the ſame time to go ſee the Water Works that were made in the Garden, and which were to be tryed for the firſt time. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, who had many other deſigns in her Head, told him, that ſhe had ſomething to do with the Queen, but that if he would in the mean time go alone, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them from playing, they would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently follow him. <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> ſeeing, that the Lady would get rid of him, anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered her that he would have the Honour of attending them: and that he well knew that there would be nothing done in the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:61828:39"/>Garden till he came. But I muſt, reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Counteſs, (in whoſe Eyes it was eaſie to ſee the Impatience ſhe was in to ſend him away) ſee the Queen, and ſpeak to her in particular. You may do it, Madam, replyed this Lover, holding ſtill ſirme, while that I attend you. But can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not you, replyed ſhe, go wait for me in the Garden. Not without you tell me, (<hi>Don Geronimo</hi> anſwered coldly, beginning to loſe his Patience) that I am troubleſome here, for I ſhould have more pleaſure in accompanying you: thereupon the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, ſeeing the <hi>Count</hi> going from the Queens, and that he paſſed by without ſtopping, ran after him. This Miniſter, whoſe Heart was ſtabbed with that acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no longer doubting of the truth of his misfortune, approached her, and with Eyes that were inflamed by his jealouſie, I ſee, Madam, ſaid he ſoftly to her, what you waited for, an other time I ſhall be more Complaiſant. The <hi>Count</hi> ſurprized with ſeeing <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> go away in a rage, not knowing, if it was with him that he was angry, asked the Counteſs what that Miniſter had ſaid to her, and from whence it came he retired in ſuch a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61828:40"/>pet. The Lady, who would not have been willing that the <hi>Count</hi> ſhould have known that <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> was in Love with her, was at firſt ſomething perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; But her Wit which never failed her upon any occaſion, furniſhing her with an anſwer to her advantage, Do not you ſee, ſaid ſhe to him with a forced ſmile, that he is a faithfull Miniſter, and that he takes part in all that concernes his Maſter? He ſaw you come alone from the Queens, with whom, you had paſſed an Hour in particular diſcourſe, and you would not, that he ſhould have Ombrage of it. You are too well made, and he would injure your merit, if he treated you with more ſoftneſs. How, Madam, cryed <hi>Hannibal,</hi> troubled at this News! Should I be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, that this man ſhould have ſo crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſuſpicions of me. Ah! Madam, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he upon the point of running after him, I muſt undeceive him as ſoon as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. Make not ſo much haſte, anſwered ſhe ſtopping him, for I have ſomething to tell you of more importance than that. Permit me firſt, replyed the <hi>Count,</hi> to ſpeak with this Miniſter, and I will after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards return to you. It will be a uſeleſs
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61828:40"/>trouble, replyed ſhe, and inſtead of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiving him, you will by this eagerneſs but<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the more confirm him in his Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions. I do not beleive that, replyed he, but in fine let what will happen I muſt needs ſpeak to him; and I begg, Madam, you will let me go. After that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs could not detain him any longer, but it was not without a very ſenſible diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. That <hi>Nicety</hi> ſhe ſaw in him in what concerned the Queen, and that ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs to run after <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> ſeemed, in giving her an extream diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, to open her Eyes for the diſcovering to her all that ſhe could imagine moſt cruel to her. What ſhould it be poſſible! Said ſhe in thinking of all this, that I ſhould have been ſo long without perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this miſtery: and that Chance ſhould have thus diſcovered it. Am I miſtaken! Or is it true that the <hi>Count</hi> is in Love with the Queen. Ah, Heavens! Added ſhe in lifting up her Eyes, can you have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared me ſo terrible a Blow. Her mind was almoſt overcome with theſe cruel thoughts, when the Queen came out of her Chamber, who told her, that ſhe had a deſire to go walk in the Garden, the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:61828:41"/>Counteſs immediately endeavoured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her ſelf, for fear that Princeſs ſhould obſerve in her Face the diſorder of her Heart; but the Queen her ſelf was ſo poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with her own thoughts, that ſhe hardly looked upon the Counteſs. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they went towards the Garden, where the Queen being deſirous to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain her ſelf all alone, left the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs behind her with the reſt of her Train. <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> who walked at the ſame time his thoughts or rather his furies in that ſame Garden, ſeeing the Queen, went directly to her, for to complain of the Counteſſes cruelty, he borded her with a melancholly air; and told her his misfortune with ſo ſad a Tone, that it would have made the Queen laugh, if ſhe had took leſs part than ſhe did in the Subject of his Complaints. She endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured however to undeceive him; Ah.! Madam, anſwered he, I am but too well perſuaded, that in employing my ſelf for your repoſe, I have only laboured to ruin my own: and that the arrival of this Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador undoes me, and that in deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you from all your pains, he loads me with the moſt cruel torments that a Heart
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61828:41"/>can ſuffer. I lived at leaſt in ſome hopes, added he ſighing, and if I was not belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I had no Rival. There are few Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this Kingdom who would have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted with me that happineſs; and am not I very unfortunate in having been my ſelf the Inſtrument of my deſpair! The Queen, who did really take pitty of this poor Lover, to whom ſhe had very great Obligations, was not in much pain to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him; that ſhe was concerned at his misfortune, and that ſhe would uſe all her power with the <hi>Count</hi> as well as with the Lady to hinder, that he might not be troubled in his deſigns. But a certain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Heart engaged her much more in it, ſhe was very glad that this intereſt was authorized by ſo reaſonable a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texte, as was that of favouring the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> as ſhe had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him. She then told him for to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him, that he needed only to retire, and that ſhe would go that very moment and ſpeak to the Counteſs, who was come with her into the Garden. This Miniſter having thereupon quitted the Queen, ſhe enquired of her Maids what was become of the Counteſs, whom ſhe ſaw not:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61828:42"/>Who anſwered her, that they beleived ſhe was in the middle <hi>Arbour</hi> with the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of <hi>Naples,</hi> this Princeſs, who had already been much concerned with what <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> had told her, was ſo troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to learn at the ſame time, that the <hi>Count</hi> was in particular Conference with her, that not being Miſtreſs of her ſelf, ſhe would go ſee what they did in ſo reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a place as that.</p>
            <p>As we are extream prone to flatter our ſelves in things which pleaſe us, we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe beleive, as late as we can, thoſe which are diſadvantageous to us; and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially Women, in whom Vanity is a weakneſs they lay by the Laſt of all others: the miſtaken Counteſs might have obſerved by all the actions of <hi>Count Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> that his Heart inclined towards the Queen, but taking pleaſure in blinding her ſelf, and not being willing that other Qualities than her own ſhould have made impreſſion upon that Lovers Heart, ſhe had perſuaded her ſelf that the devoir of an Ambaſſador bound him to that Princeſs, and that of a Lover to her, till the Affair of <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> in which beſides the earneſtneſs he had been in to run after
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:61828:42"/>him; ſhe had immediately obſerved a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain trouble in his Face, which had more of the Character of a paſſionate Lover than of an Ambaſſador zealous for the Queens Intereſts. Theſe thoughts which had accompanyed her to the Garden, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conducted her into the <hi>Green-Arbour,</hi> after ſhe had ſeen <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> bord the Queen, entertained her in a profound penſiveneſs, when the <hi>Count,</hi> who ſtill ſought that Miniſter, paſſing by the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> fancyed that in ſeeing the Counteſs the Queen was there, and went in to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute her, however finding only the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, who ſitting upon a Graſs ſeat, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by her languiſhing poſture to have ſought retreat, asked her Pardon for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving interrupted her in her Solitude, and was going to retire. But ſhe roſe, and eying him with a Face mingled with vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Love, I very well ſee, My Lord, ſaid ſhe to him that it is not me you come to ſeek here. It is true. Madam, anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered the <hi>Count,</hi> that I ſtill ſeek for <hi>Don Geronimo:</hi> and perhaps the Queen, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted ſhe, but whether the Queen or <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> added ſhe bluſhing, it would be neither obliging nor civil to find
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:61828:43"/>me alone, and to quit me again to run after a man. I muſt tell you, purſued ſhe, that he is in conference with that Princeſs, and that you will loſe nothing by being a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with me. <hi>Hannibal</hi> yielding at the reproaches of the Counteſs, whom he had no mind to diſpleaſe, prepared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to entertain her; and the Counteſs, who had already made ſo many advances, continuing her deſign, <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> is not the only perſon that is jealous of your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alone to the Queens, and that you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain her without witneſſes: there are People who have obſerved your actions yet more nearly; and who, taking more intereſt than he in your ſighs, have puſhed their Penetration ſo far, that they fancy they have found out their courſe; and you will be more troubled to undeceive them than this Miniſter. The <hi>Count</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſurprized with the diſcourſe of that Lady, who ſpake to him very ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, aſſured her, that he could hardly beleive what ſhe told him; becauſe he did not think he had ever given the leaſt ground for the like ſuſpicions. I will not tell you, replyed the Counteſs upon what they have particularly conjectured, that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:61828:43"/>your Heart went towards the Queen: but there is perceived in you an air ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly amorous; ſighs eſcape from you from time to time before People: you fall into languiſhings and into abſences of mind, and to the leaſt of your actions all is ſo paſſionate in you, that one would really ſay you were in Love with all the World. In the mean time, as there is not in this Court many perſons fair enough for a man ſo well made as you, they eaſily caſt their conjectures upon thoſe you ſee moſt often, who are the Queen and my ſelf. The moſt common Opinion is, and with reaſon, that it is the Queen, but that Princeſs will have it me. She endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours at leaſt to perſwade <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> ſo, who ſeems to take more intereſt in it than ought to be permitted to ſuch a man as he. I explain my ſelf no more, my Lord (purſued ſhe) it is for you to draw ſuch Conſequences as you pleaſe; but it is to debaſe one's ſelf very much, for a Queen to manage ſuch a man to my coſt. I will not, added ſhe, pretend to an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that is not my due; wherefore I begg of you that in undeceiving <hi>Don Geroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> of the ſuſpicions he has of you upon the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61828:44"/>account of that Princeſs, you would not let him know that it is to me you addreſs your paſſion: for I am not at all of the Humour to take pleaſure in being made uſe of for a Pretexte. The <hi>Count,</hi> much perplexed at this diſcourſe, fell into the ſnare that the Counteſs laid for him; and as if he was awaked from a long ſleep. Can it be poſſible, faid he ſighing, that this Miniſter durſt lift his Eyes upon the Queen, and that this Princeſs— no, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he, after a moment of reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this cannot be: I know, purſued he with ſome tranſport, the Queens Heart, and though the inſolence of ſuch a man as he ſhould have mounted to that point he —But, my Lord, (interrupted the Counteſs, whom that diſcourſe aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) Is it againſt me that you ought to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute this? and do I ask you If it is true, that <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Geronimo</hi> is in Love with the Queen or no? It is of you, purſued ſhe, the diſcourſe was of, and I intereſs my ſelf in it more than ordinary, I ſhall not oppoſe all that can be ſaid, if you love me as they ſay you do, the paſſion of ſuch a man as you, has ever wherewith to flatter the Vanity of a Woman, not to be diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61828:44"/>at the report of it; but if it is the Queen you Love, as I do not at all doubt, your Generoſity is concerned not to ſuffer me to be played upon.</p>
            <p>She was come to that, and the <hi>Count</hi> who fell from perplexity to perplexity, knew not what to anſwer, when the Queen entring the <hi>Arbour</hi> ſo ſurprized the Counteſs, that not knowing how to hide the diſorder the <hi>Counts</hi> ſilence had caſt her in, as well as the preſence of that Princeſs, ſhe choſe to retire. The Queen ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſurprized to ſee her go away in that manner, would have called her, but in the Agitation and trouble ſhe came, ſhe found her ſelf ſo weak at her enterance, that ſhe had not the power to open her mouth. The <hi>Count,</hi> who ſaw her ſo pale and changed, run immediately to her, and with a tenderneſs full of allarum, he asked her, if ſhe found her ſelf ill, and if ſhe deſired, he would call any of her Maids. No, anſwered ſhe him, in ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a languiſhing air: But from whence comes it that the Counteſs goes away? I know not, Madam, anſwered the <hi>Count</hi> in a manner ſomething perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. You know not, replyed the Princeſs;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:61828:45"/>I believe however you can tell me the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon if you will, but I begin, added ſhe, to know the little relyance there is to be had upon you, by the little Confidence you have in me, Alas! with what do you reproach me, Madam, cryed that Lover? and how little you Penetrate how far goes—he ſtopped there ſighing, and on a ſuddain renewing the diſcourſe with ſomething more heat, if my Life was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, Madam, added he, I ſhould not heſitate one moment the telling you all there is in my Heart. Why then, reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhe, do you refuſe me the part I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in your Confidence? You know, Madam, anſwered the <hi>Count</hi> what you forbid me? Yes, but I no longer forbid it you, replyed ſhe, how ſhould I know what you would think? For if it is what they would make me beleive, it would ſeem that in leaving you in this ſilence one ſhould authorize your temerity: No, <hi>Count,</hi> purſued ſhe, with a more preſſing manner than ever, you ſhall tell me, I Command it you, if your Heart does not accuſe you of any thing againſt me: if the ſentiments you have for me are as full of reſpect, as I could deſire them of you.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61828:45"/>You are troubled, <hi>Count,</hi> continued ſhe ſtill, ſeeing the diſorder into which ſhe put him; and your Face does but too much declare that you are Guilty. Do not rely upon my goodneſs, I have a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for you, becauſe you have ſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; but I am to maintain my Glory; a ſmall thing would wound it, and you would leſs deſerve favour than any one ſoever, if you were fallen into ſuch a misfortune. The amorous <hi>Hannibal,</hi> with a Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſad and full of reſpect, though ever very paſſionate, I have failed, Madam, I confeſs it, ſaid he to her ſighing, without being able to ſay any thing more: at which that lovely Princeſs extreamly touched, began to repreſent to him with a great deal of ſoftneſs, that ſhe was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a Rank nor in a State to ſuffer that any other than the King her Husband ſhould have ſuch ſentiments for her; and that if he was reaſonable, he would do himſelf juſtice in that point, and not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himſelf to be hurryed away by a blind paſſion and without hopes. That he very well knew that it was to loſe his reſpect to her, and that ſince ſhe had perceived it, what ſhe owed to her ſelf would oblige
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:61828:46"/>her, not only to forbid him her preſence, but alſo to cauſe him to be recalled by the King her Father, if the hopes ſhe had of reducing him to his devoir, did not make her treat him with a little more goodneſs: that this merited, that he ſhould make ſome reflection upon it, and that he would ſeriouſly labour to cure his mind of a blindneſs, which could not fail in the end of being his ruine. I know, Madam, anſwered that Lover, who began to take Courage, that I have merited Death, I ſhall not refuſe it at any time you ſhall be pleaſed to order it me, but for loving you nothing can hinder me as long as I live. I might not tell it you, as I did not during the ſpace of Five Years, that I have loved you with a paſſion the moſt tender and fulleſt of reſpect that ever one loved with, I might likewiſe not ſee you, that neither my Eyes nor ſighs ſhould ſpeak; but I ſhould not however have failed of having alwaies for you the ſame ardour, and it does not depend on me to get rid of it. I have told my ſelf, all that can be ſaid in that caſe. I have ſet before my Eyes greater unhappineſses than all thoſe you can ever threaten me with: and all this,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:61828:46"/>Madam, has but the more irritated my paſſion. All the reaſons contrary to this inclination, and even to your very hatred, which would be to me the moſt redoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thing in the World, have never been able to perſuade me, that you were not the moſt lovely Princeſs under the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and that I ought to love you to the very Grave. I ſaw it was without hopes, purſued he, ſeeing that the Queen let him ſpeak, I durſt not even flatter my ſelf, that you could ever know any thing of it, and yet I could not hinder the aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning my ſelf to it, as if I were to have been the moſt happy of all Lovers. The Queen who had thitherto ſuffered her ſelf to be lulled with the pleaſure of hearing him, recovering from ſo charming an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, was ſomething aſhamed of her weakneſs and bluſht. Whereupon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calling all the efforts that modeſty and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voir could make upon her, and taking an air more ſevere than the ſoftneſs of her Nature, and than even the tenderneſs of her Heart could well permit her, You only ſeek then to irritate me againſt you, and what advice ſoever I can give you, you will deſpiſe it, and you fear not my anger.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61828:47"/>I fear all from you, Madam, anſwered he with a tranſported voice, but what I ought moſt to ſear in you is your fair Eyes. And would to God, added he ſighing, that I had ever ſeen you in anger and full of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain and contempt for me. This wiſh ſo little uſual, and the action with which that Lover pronounced theſe words ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſomething ſo rare to the Queen, that notwithſtanding all her affected ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, ſhe could hardly hold from laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not being willing to purſue a diſcourſe, from which ſhe ſaw ſhe ſhould not come of on her ſide with that haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that what the <hi>Count</hi> told her merited, ſhe roſe, and without looking upon him, I have nothing elſe to ſay to you, ſaid ſhe to him, without it be that you make uſe of the advice I have given you, for you may very well judge, purſued ſhe in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of that <hi>Arbour,</hi> that I can no longer ſee you with modeſty and without doing an injury to my Glory, if you ſtil continue in the ſame Sentiments. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore change them, added ſhe, if you would have me live with you as I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto done. You muſt then, Madam learn me how to hate you. For to hate
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:61828:47"/>me, No, replyed the Queen, but there is a Temperament between both that I could pardon in you. Ah! Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed this Lover, how difficult is that Temperament to keep with ſuch a Perſon as you. I believe, purſued he, that if it was poſſible not to Love you with that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs that I Love you, I ſhould hate you more than ever any one was hated: The Queen fell a ſmiling and viewing him, I muſt then be extreamly hated in the World. For I aſſure my ſelf there are few People in the World that are bold enough to Love me as you ſay. If all the Earth knew you as well as I do, Madam, replyed immediately the <hi>Count</hi> with a Tone full of Ardour, all the Earth would adore you, or hate you, as the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Princeſs in the World, who after having forced Hearts to dye for Love of you, takes delight in making them dye of deſpair. The Queen looking upon him with a great deal of Complaiſance, cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſaid ſhe is not my Vice, but I know what I owe my ſelf, and who go againſt that, added ſhe a little more ſeriouſly, may aſſure themſelves of not being very happy. They were then come to her
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61828:48"/>apartment, where the King being entred, the <hi>Count</hi> retired little ſatisfi'd with theſe laſt words, but likewiſe leſs unhappy than he could have hoped after ſuch a declaration.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs, who had paſſed all that time in her Chamber, in examining in her mind, all the <hi>Count</hi>'s words and actions, found to the leaſt ſtroak in that Lover, that ſhe had been unluckily miſtaken, and that the Queens Charmes poſſeſſed him abſolutely. Cruel diſcoveries when they come ſo late; ſhe had no hopes but the Princeſses kindneſs, who making per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome difficulty to Embark her ſelf in an engagement of Heart which would ruin her, would be in no pain to make her that Sacrifice. Wherefore ſhe reſolved without waiting any longer, to ſpeak to her of it, to open to her entirely her Heart, that ſhe might the more eaſily move her by her pains. She came to her at the ſame time the <hi>Count</hi> left her, and caſting her ſelf immediately upon her knees, with a Torrent of Tears, that ſhe ſhed, ſhe was ſome time without being able to expreſs a Word: At which the Queen much aſtoniſhed and concerned, asked her ſeveral times what it was ſo much
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:61828:48"/>afflicted her. Alas! what it is, Madam, anſwered ſhe with a profound ſigh. I am the moſt unhappy Creture under the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens: I ſee my Death cauſed by the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the World I Love the moſt. Yes my Queen, purſued ſhe, in recovering her ſelf a little, it is a ſecret I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto concealed from you, but for which I am very cruelly puniſhed, not to have occaſion to draw ſtill upon me your reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. I have ſuffered my ſelf to be ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by the Courtſhip of the <hi>Count d' Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line,</hi> I took for my ſelf the ſighs I ſaw him make, and I fancied he ſpoak to me, when he only thought of you. Of me, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the Queen. Yes, Madam, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued the Counteſs, it is you that take him from me, and that which is moſt cruel to me is that it is you, whom I cannot hate, who are the cauſe of all my ills. The Queen, having asked her upon what ſhe founded theſe ſuſpicions, Alas! Would to God, anſwered ſhe lamentably, that I could doubt of it, but I am but too well convinced; my hopes, Madam, is now only in you, and if you allow the ſighs of that Lover, I have only Death to deliver me from all my pains. In finiſhing theſe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61828:49"/>laſt Words her Tears trickled down in greater abundance than ever: The Queen, who had the tendereſt Soul of the World, was ſo touched to ſee her in that ſtate, that ſhe wiſhed, in that moment, ſhe had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen the <hi>Count,</hi> and was ſome time without being able to ſay any thing to her, being aſſailed by a Thouſand different mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which were at length followed by ſome Tears, which ſhe could not hinder her ſelf from ſhedding, whether it was from the Effort ſhe made upon her ſelf, for the reſiſting the Sentiments of her Heart, or from the pitty ſhe had of thoſe of the Counteſs, I cannot, ſaid ſhe to her, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my being beloved, if I am beloved againſt my will; but all that can be done in that I will do it, and you ſhall be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it to Morrow. While that this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation paſſed in the Queens Cabinet, there was one much more extraordinary in <hi>Count Hannibals</hi> Chamber, <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> who had learnt that that Ambaſſador had a long time ſought for him, would make uſe of that Pretexte to go know what he deſired of him, and to acquaint himſelf at the ſame time with his Sentiments upon the inclination of his Heart, for having
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:61828:49"/>well examined him, he did not find, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was diſſimulation or a reall indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that he perfectly anſwered the eagerneſs of the Counteſs. And for the better acting his part he reſolved to feign he was in Love with the Queen, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that the <hi>Count</hi> would open him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf yet the more freely to him: Inſomuch that being come to his apartment, ſeeing that the Ambaſſador did not ſpeak to him of any thing, and that he was poſſeſſed with a Melancholly, that rendred to him Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation troubleſome and incommode; I perceive, my Lord, ſaid he to him, that I have ill taken my time, for the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring you a Viſit; but being told that you ſought for me, I fancied I could not be diſpenſed from coming to ask you, what you deſired of a man who is entirely yours. The <hi>Count</hi> Civilly thanked him; and continuing in his ſad Humour, he anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered him coldly, that it was nothing, and that he had been only told, that he obſerved his ſteps, of which he was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to have known the reaſon; but that he no longer cared for it. He ſpoak to him with this indifference for the better undeceiving him. As you are here, my
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:61828:50"/>Lord, independant of whom ſoever, and that you are not to give an account of your actions to any one, neither is there any one that would concern themſelves with examining them; but you cannot hinder that when one has Pretentions in a place, they fear to have a Concurrent made like you. Not that, added he, that I have hitherto had wherewith per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to Ground my judgments: You are ſeen to go in ſeveral places; you have aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duities for ſeveral perſons, and perhaps, if one could know the party your Heart takes, one ſhould be at eaſe and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſerve you in it. The <hi>Count</hi> who knew he had to do with a Cunning Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, was upon his Guard, but as he haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arded nothing in acting the Counteſſes Lover, and that it would be on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary a means for the entring into his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, if it was true as they would make him beleive, that he was in Love with the Queen, he confeſſed to him in a confiding way, that being to paſs ſome daies in the Court of <hi>Majorca,</hi> he had thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the divertiſement of a man of his Humour, to have an Amuſement of Heart, and that he had caſt his Eyes upon
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:61828:50"/>the Counteſs, but that, if he had the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt deſign there, he was ready to aband <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her entirely to him; not pretending to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake an engagement of Conſequence in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lace, where he was to ſtay ſo little a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime. <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> felt to the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of his Heart the cruel grief of that declaration, and compoſing his Face the beſt he could, he told him, with a joy he was not a little troubled to feign, that he learnt with an extream pleaſure the Courſe of his Heart; that he ſhould have had the ſame defference in his regard, if he had been ſo unfortunate as to have had the ſame Inclinations with him, but that, ſince their vows had different Objects, they might without trouble each on his ſide render their amourous devoirs; that he promiſed him not to diſturb him in his, and that he hoped the ſame favour from him: and thereupon quitted him, ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that in the violence he uſed upon himſelf, he could no longer maintain that part. The <hi>Count</hi> had yielded to him wiſh too much Facility the intereſts he had in the Counteſs, for to beleive it was in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt: it is not ſo eaſie to lay by that paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, provided one is really engaged in it,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:61828:51"/>and this generous proceedure of his Rival appeared to him too full of Art, for to be perſuaded that it was ſincere: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he would return him the ſame Complement, and went from him with all the rage of a Lover Tranſported with jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies. The Queen, who had promiſed the Counteſs to contribute as much as ſhe could to her repoſe, no ſooner ſaw her ſelf rid of her, than that her Heart com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining that ſhe had ſo little conſulted it in the moſt important Affair of her Life, had like by many ſighs and regrets to have overturned all that pitty had exacted in the Counteſſes favour, for it is rarely we betray our ſelves, and leſs in Love than in any other thing: But Glory maintaining the firſt Party, ſeconded with a Thouſand reaſons of the Conſequences and the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, again balanced the Sentiments of her Soul, and ſo well confirmed her in her firſt deſign as the moſt becoming her, that ſhe did nothing all the reſt of the Day and all the Night than ſeek reaſons for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying her ſelf againſt the weakneſs of her Heart. She was almoſt in this diſpoſition when the Counteſs, with whom ſhe had regulated the meaſures ſhe would take,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:61828:51"/>for the yielding to her entirely the <hi>Count,</hi> came to give her notice that that Lover was juſt a coming. The Queen made her lide her ſelf in her Cabinet, and having given orders to a Page to bring in the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of <hi>Naples</hi> when he ſhould come, ſhe prepared her ſelf for an engagement, in which the trembling which had took her, ſince her Lady of Honour had ſpoke to her of the <hi>Count,</hi> made her fear ſhe ſhould not come of with that caſe as ſhe had promiſed her ſelf. <hi>Hannibal</hi> appeared with a Face ſad and melancholly, and which ſtill ſeemed ſenſible of the words, with which the Princeſs had left him the day before. She could not ſee him without being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; and as if ſhe had forgot the cruel deſign ſhe had againſt him, ſhe asked him in a Charming manner, from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the ſadneſs ſhe ſaw upon his Face. A Man, Madam, anſwered he, ſo unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate as I am, cannot bear a Gay look. But unfortunate, replyed the Queen, thoſe are not to be pityed, who will be ſo: It is true, Madam, anſwered that Lover, that I ſhould not be pityed to Love the moſt inſenſible Princeſs of the Earth, for it is a long time ſince I prepared
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:61828:52"/>my ſelf for it; But I am—added he ſighing, and ſtopped there. Whereupon the Queen, who would not be more curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, than was neceſſary in that occaſion, without preſſing him to make an end, muſt you not confeſs, ſaid ſhe to him, that you have loſt your reaſon in applying your ſelf to an object, where not only you have no hopes; but where you are even forbid to pretend to any, and which is capable of ruining you with thoſe, whom duty ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges you to conſider more than all things. Ah! Madam, cryed the amourous <hi>Count</hi> ſoftly, thoſe are not my greateſt misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes: And would to God, added he, ſomething raiſing his voice, that at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of that reaſon, that you ſay, Madam, I have loſt, I had only your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility to fear or the ruine of my For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. Believe me, <hi>Count,</hi> interrupted that Princeſs, whoſe Heart was touched with all he ſaid, follow an advice that I will give you as a true Friend, lay by a paſſion as extravagant as uſeleſs, and turn your thoughts towards an Object, who ſhall be of a Rank and in Right of acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging them. The Counteſs of <hi>Palo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>—at that Name <hi>Hannibal,</hi> retired
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:61828:52"/>two ſteps, and would have interrupted the Queen, but ſhe making a ſign to him to let her purſue, continued in this manner, ſhe is of one of the moſt illuſtrious Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſhe is a Lady who has Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Wit to ſurpaſs all Women I have ever ſeen; and if I was a Man, none could pleaſe me ſo much as ſhe, ſee her, offer her that tenderneſs and Heart, of which ſhe can make a better uſe than I, and you will certainly be happy. I, Madam, anſwered the <hi>Count,</hi> who had heard very impatiently that cruel Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the end, could I ever Love any one after you, when I ſhould be capable of ceaſing to Love you. Ah! Madam, continued he ſighing, know me better, all the misfortunes of the Earth ſhould ſooner fall upon me than I would once think of it: It is however the only means, replyed the Queen, to live well with me. I begg it of you, and if that be not enough I Command you, as much as I can have power over you. I ſhall reckon for my ſelf the cares and the Paces you ſhall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy for her, and as much as your former ſighs may have given me pain, ſo much this little Sacrafice that you ſhall make to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:61828:53"/>my Glory, will give me joy. If I am not, Madam, replyed ſadly the deſolate <hi>Count,</hi> to merit your favour but by that: if I cannot, purſued he ſighing, pleaſe you but by quitting you for another, I am to be the moſt unhappy of all men, and am going to draw upon my ſelf your hatred for all the reſt of my daies. For it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for me to obey you therein; Or for me, <hi>Count,</hi> replyed immediately the Queen riſing, to ſee you any more: think of it better, added ſhe, for the vertue of a Princeſs as I am, would ſuffer by it too much, after the Liberty you have taken, Ah, Cruel Princeſs, cryed then the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate <hi>Hannibal</hi> in a Tranſported manner, how can an Innocent Love as mine be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to your Glory, it having neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires nor hopes, why add you to the Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of not ſuffering that I Love you, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of making me Love againſt my will, what I can never Love. The Queen not being willing to puſh any farther a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation which was as ſenſible for her, as it was Cruel for that Lover. It is enough, ſaid ſhe to him; defferences that one has for what one Loves, are the ſecret marks of a true Love, and I ſhall know
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:61828:53"/>yours by the Obedience you ſhall ſhew me in what I deſire of you. Love does not deſtroy it ſelf, Madam, anſwered the <hi>Count,</hi> but I ſee what it is, and what you deſire of me. It is my Death: I ſhall not be put to much trouble to ſatisfy you therein. In finiſhing theſe words he quitted the Queen with ſo diſordered a look, that that Princeſs really fearing ſome terible effect from his deſpair, ſent a Page to recal him and letting her ſelf fall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing upon her Bed, near which ſhe was ſeated; Ah, Heavens! Cryed ſhe to what Combats do you deliver me, when the Counteſs coming out of the Cabinet where ſhe had been hid, caſt her ſelf upon her Knees with Eyes all filled with Tears: Too generous Princeſs, ſaid ſhe to her, how can I acknowledge ſo much goodneſs? You maintain the deſigns of a Creature, who merits rather your hatred than your favour: and for her ſake you bring into deſpair a man who adores you. She would have continued ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but the Page the Queen had ſent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Count,</hi> reentring, told her, that the Ambaſſador of <hi>Naples</hi> was coming back: Inſomuch that the Counteſs, who
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:61828:54"/>would not have been willing he ſhould have ſeen her in the State ſhe was, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned immediately into the Cabinet, where being entred, the <hi>Count</hi> arrived, who ſaw it ſhut with much Precipitation. His ſurprize was great: for he had not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved there had been any one with the Queen; and his jealouſie, which, after the laſt Converſation he had had with <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> was yet augmented by the Order or the Counſel, that that Princeſs had juſt given him, of ceaſing to Love her, for to give himſelf to the Counteſs of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomer,</hi> increaſed more than ever, with ſeeing that Door ſhut, he believed it was ſome one who ought to be ſuſpected to him, and to whom the Queen had had a mind to Sacrifice him. That Princeſs who got up in ſeeing him enter, obſerving, that he had his Eyes towards that Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, and that he conſidered it with the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of a man, who ruminated ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in his mind, immediately fancied he had ſeen the Counteſs, and that he ſuſpected the Trick that had been played him. She would ſee, what he would ſay of it; But as he was ſtill in a profound penſivenſs, you are ſurprized, ſaid ſhe to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:61828:54"/>him ready to Laugh, though ſhe was but little difpoſed to it, at the Ambuſcade that has been laid you. It is true: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, anſwered that Lover, that I ſhould never have imagined, that you would have had ſuch a Converſation as we have had for the ſavouring another: I know not, at leaſt, continued he, by what I have me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited this deceipt. Do you call deceipt, (replyed the Queen ſtill Laughing, who really believed he meant the Counteſs,) an Innocent deſign one has of ſerving the Perſon one Loves. But the <hi>Count</hi> who at firſt caſt his ſuſpicions upon <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> whom he fancied to be conceal'd in that Cabinet, was overcome with grief at that Confeſſion, after which he could no longer doubt of his misfortune, and chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Colour Two or Three times, before he could anſwer her; No, Madam, ſaid he to her, viewing her with Eyes fuller of vexation than Love, I ſhall give what name you pleaſe to the moſt cruel injury that can be done a man: but the Triumph was already great enough, without calling me back for the puſhing it farther; and take it not ill, Madam, if I no longer ſerve for a Victimeto aman ſo
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:61828:55"/>little worthy of one of my kind. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon making a Low Bow to the Queen, he went out of the Chamber with a Heart as full of rage, as it had before been ſeized with grief, leaving the Queen much in pain, to divine what man he meant, and what obliged him to retire in that manner, without ever being able to divine the true Subject. The Counteſs, who was come out of that Cabinet, and who had not failed to penetrate into the <hi>Counts</hi> jealouſie, having been the firſt who inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him with it, might have eaſily drawn the Queen from the perplexity ſhe was in, but ſhe would not reveal to her a ſecret, from which ſhe hoped to draw ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. The greateſt Friendſhip of Women is not proof againſt Treachery when it is Love that inſpires it. It has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies more appearance than reality. It is not to be relyed upon, the leaſt intereſt of Heart ſtifles it, or makes it ſerve its deſigns. The Queen after having enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained her ſelf ſome time with the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, finding her Heart in need of a little ſolitude, took the pretexte, to rid her ſelf of her, that ſhe was not well, and that ſhe deſired to take ſome repoſe. Theſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:61828:55"/>two fair Lovers had their pains and their cares, it is true, that the Queen was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, and that this point in Love is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſolacing a great many ills, but Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Devoir which ſhe had inceſſantly before her Eyes for the Combating an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination which forced her away, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this the Cruelty of cauſing all the unhappineſs of a man, whoſe Felicity ſhe would have procured; to feign not to Love him; and not to be willing to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, when that ſhe really found that all her tenderneſs was for him, and that ſhe was Charmed with his, and in fine to be condemned to perſuade him by all manner of reaſons to Love another, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps would have made her deſperate: all this, I ſay, made appear that the Deſtiny contrary to the repoſe of great Souls, had taken pleaſure to produce Caprichious and oppoſite motions in the Heart of that Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Princeſs. The unfortunate Counteſs paſſed her time no more agreeably than ſhe, if ſhe felt not all thoſe ſtinging pains which Devoir and Glory occaſion, in oppoſing the paſſion of a Heart, ſhe had likewiſe only her revenge to ſolace her in the rage of ſeeing her ſelf contemned. She waited
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:61828:56"/>with great impatience all the reſt of the Day, to ſee the <hi>Count</hi> again, for the quite confounding him upon the Subject of <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> but he appeared not at Court, and ſhe eaſily comprehended what was the occaſion of his retreat. She was no ſooner up the day after, than that ſhe ſent to tell him, that ſhe had ſomething of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to acquaint him with, and that if he would take the time that the King and Queen were at Dinner, he would find her in her Chamber. <hi>Hannibal,</hi> who ſince the Queen had propoſed to him to Love the Counteſs, had took an Averſion for that Lady, whom he conſidered, as one does a Mortal Enemy, would hardly have gone to the aſſignation ſhe made him, if in the deſpair he was, the Curioſity of knowing, if it was not ſomething from the Queen ſhe had to tell him, had not overcome that averſion. He went to her at the Hour appointed; but with a Face ſo ſad and changed, that it ſurprized the Counteſs. I take pitty, my Lord, ſaid ſhe to him, of the pains you ſuffer for my ſake, and which only put me into Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. I know not, purſued ſhe, what the Queens deſign is, but ſhe might have ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:61828:56"/>her ſelf and you to ſo great a perplexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. If you were to Love me, it is not to her that I would have the Obligation of your Heart: it is an ill augure to receive that of a Man from the hand of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. It muſt give it ſelf, my Lord, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhe, uſe not conſtraint upon your ſelf for that: I made known to the Queen Yeſterday, that I was not obliged to her for all theſe cares, as it is not to do me a kindneſs ſhe takes ſo much trouble, but for the Love of a man, who came to make a Triumph to me of the Sacrifice ſhe had made him of your paſſion; It is from <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> at leaſt that I know all that I here tell you. He related to me to the very leaſt particulars of the Converſation you had with the Queen, which he heard in the Cabinet he was concealed. The <hi>Count</hi> found his grief terribly renewed at this recital; but that which gave him moſt pain was the Vanity of his Rival, who thus triumphed over his misfortune: Wherefore he could not hold from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, likewiſe ſeeing, that it would be uſeleſs any longer to conceal his paſſion to a Lady who knew too much of it, but it was ſtill without ever loſing the reſpect he
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:61828:57"/>owed the Queen, complaining more of his Deſtiny than of the unjuſt Preference of that Princeſs, who deſpiſed him for ſuch a man as <hi>Don Geronimo.</hi> The Counteſs, who would have been glad he had puſhed his reſentment farther, forgot nothing that might heighten the injury that was done him, ſometimes excuſing the Queen upon the acknowledgment ſhe owed that Miniſter, for the ſervices ſhe had received from him, and which might have toucht her Heart. This laſt ſtroke made that ſad Lover quite deſperate who ſaw ſome reaſon in what was told him; but nothing however that could oblige him to rail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Princeſs. There never eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from him one word, which was not in all the ſubmiſſion of a Lover full of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect: On the contrary the more reaſon he had to complain of her, the more he made appear his tenderneſs, reſolving, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſo much contempt and ſo many Cruelties, to Love her till Death. The Counteſs, in whoſe Heart all theſe Sentiments were ſo many ſtabs, ſuffering pains which only a Jealous and Paſſionate Woman can imagine, ſeeing that ſhe could not ſucceed on that ſide, I am, my Lord,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:61828:57"/>ſaid ſhe to him, as much intereſſed as you in the Queens Conduct; for ſhe may have ſome reaſon with you to treat you after the manner ſhe does, but with me, ſhe has none, I know the means, purſued ſhe, if you would beleive me, to get into her favour, if ſhe has the leaſt diſpoſition not to hate you, and for me to have my return on <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> by whom I have been played upon. Do you make ſhew of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me, and that you have followed the Councels that were given you. A Woman, added ſhe, may uſe contempt, but ſhe ſeldom ſees without vexation that an other does profit by it. It is the only touch ſtone for the Queens Heart, and I warrant you, that this fiction ſhall have laſted no longer than Eight daies, than that you will ſee her change her Opinion. To feign for Eight daies, replyed the <hi>Count,</hi> who liked the Councel well enough that the Counteſs gave him, it is a great deal of time, Madam, for a Lover, who is full of Ardour for that Charming Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. He had hardly finiſhed ſpeaking, than that the Queen returning from din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, paſſed through the Counteſſes Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and was much ſurprized to find the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:61828:58"/>
               <hi>Count</hi> with her at that Hour. That Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, who would begin to act the part he was adviſed to by the Counteſs, no ſooner ſaw her arrive, than that riſing, he reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, thinking himſelf much more ſtrong to ſeign, in flying an object that he ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, notwithſtanding all her cruel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, than in remaining in her preſence. The Queen ſtill more aſtoniſhed to ſee the <hi>Count</hi> go thus away, asked her I ady of Honour the reaſon of it, who declared ſhe knew nothing, but in ſuch a manner that it excited that Princeſſes Curioſity, who preſſed her to tell her the Subject of that prompt retreat, and upon what they diſcourſed. The Counteſs after having ſtill made ſome refuſal for the augmenting the Queens ſuſpicions, feigning to yield to ſo many Prayers, avouched to her that at length the deſpair ſhe had brought the <hi>Count</hi> to, had had the effect ſhe deſired, and that having ſought for her all the Morning to ſpeak to her in particular, he had ſaid to her ſuch things that he muſt be the moſt perfidious of all men, if they were not true. The Queen, who was not uſed be conſtrained, could not hinder from ſhowing the alteration in her Face,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:61828:58"/>that, what the Counteſs had told had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in her Heart, and opening her Mouth with much pain, ſhe asked her what it was the Ambaſſador had ſaid to her. But the Counteſs pretending to diſcretion, begged ſhe would not preſs her in that, becauſe ſhe had promiſed ſecrecy. The Queen, who would not diſcover her trouble, quitted her to retire to her Chamber, where all the moſt cruel mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions aſſailed her, and gave her no repoſe till ſhe had ſpoken in particular with the <hi>Count,</hi> but ſhe did not ſo quickly find the occaſion; for ſhe was not willing to ſpeak to him before the Counteſs, who being at length fallen ill through the agitations of her mind, and the violences ſhe was obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to uſe upon her ſelf, the <hi>Count</hi> paſſed almoſt whole daies in her Chamber. The Queen came there ſometimes, but beſides her Rival's Eyes, whom ſhe begun to fear, there was likewiſe thoſe of <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> who was from Morning to Evening in her Chamber, and whom ſhe feared as much as the Counteſs. Inſomuch that it was the rareſt Scene imaginable which dayly paſſed between thoſe Four Perſons, the <hi>Count</hi> affecting to entertain the Counteſs,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:61828:59"/>as in obedience to the Queens orders, and the Queen to diſcourſe with <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> for the amuſing him, and making the others beleive that ſhe was not concerned at their goood Intelligence. But all theſe parts, eſpecially thoſe of the Queen and the <hi>Count</hi> demanded too much violence, to laſt long: Inſomuch that the Queen one day ſinding, that <hi>Don Gerenimo</hi> was with the Counteſs, whom he endeavoured to entertain, and that the <hi>Count</hi> was at ſome diſtance, ſhe came and ſat near the place where he was, and viewing him with a tender air. What change is this, ſaid ſhe to him with a Tone of voice not to be underſtood by the Counteſs, there is in you ſince ſome daies, I can hardly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, it is the ſame <hi>Count d' Aveline,</hi> who ſpoke to me in the Garden. It is true, Madam, anſwered that Lover, wholly Charmed with this reproach, that the change is great, but it ought not to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize you, ſince you ordered me it, Yes, replyed ſhe, but confeſs you were not in much pain to obey me. The amourous <hi>Hannibal</hi> ſighed, and ſelt his Heart ſo ſeized with joy and tenderneſs, to read in the Queens Eyes, as well as in her words
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:61828:59"/>that he was not indifferent to her, that he could hardly open his mouth, to make her underſtand that ſhe was miſtaken, and that far from having changed, he loved her more paſſionately than he had ever lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her. That Lovely Princeſs well jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that that was not a place for reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, left of this diſcourſe and turning towards <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> ſhe entred into that that Miniſter had with the Countefs, not to give them matter of Suſpicion. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever after having been ſome time in that Chamber, the impatience ſhe was in of entertaining the <hi>Count</hi> in particular, maſtering all manner of conſideration, ſhe told him ſoftly, that ſhe had ſomething to ſay to him, and that he ſhould be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an Hour in the Garden; but that it might be in ſuch a manner that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs might know nothing of it. After which ſhe retired: That happy Lover wholly Charmed with this order, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at this Randevouze, could hardly hinder himſelf from ſhowing his joy before a jealous Woman, who, in the uneaſineſs ſhe was to know what the Queen had told him, examined him in all kinds. But in fine the amorous <hi>Hannibal</hi> weary of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:61828:60"/>and impatient to go to the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ſeeing the Hour approach, took leave of her, and leaving her with <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> ſeemed to ſly to the place of aſſignation, ſo fearfull he was of coming too late. Thus was he at Liberty of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a looſe to all his joy, he went from Alley to Alley, he walked, he ſtopt, he ran, he went in a Thouſand kind of Paces tranſported with the happineſs of hat day. If any thing was capable of troubling him in his amorous diſorder, it was the reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he ſometimes made on <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> whom he ſancied if not ſavoured, at leaſt very far advanced in the kindneſs of that Princeſs, who did, he thought, things for that Miniſter, that one does not for an indifferent Perſon, and for whom one has not a great engagement, he hoped to know ſuddainly the certainty. He had already took ſeveral turnes in the Garden, in thoſe occaſions time laſts furiouſly to a Lover, it was ſomething late, he inceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly turned his Eyes towards the Palace for to ſee if the Queen did not appear, and he began to doubt of his good fortune with a vexation that made him repay with great uſury the little joy he had had.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:61828:60"/>When in ſine he ſaw that lovely Princeſs come, who followed only by two of her Maids of Honour, ſhowed the earneſtneſs enough ſhe had to joyn him by the ſwift pace ſhe walked, ſhe immediately feigned to be ſurprirized with ſeeing him; How ſo late, my Lord, ſaid ſhe to him, and walking all alone in the Garden? You muſt needs be in Love to do this. The <hi>Count,</hi> who preſently comprehended the reaſon that made the Queen ſpeak thus, and that it was by reaſon of her Maids, made ſuch an anſwer as the Conjuncture demanded, and having given her his Hand to help her to walk, they began it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Queen no ſooner ſaw her ſelf at a diſtance great enough, not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by her two Maids, who followed her, than with a ſmile perfectly Charming, I have made you waite a little, ſaid ſhe to the <hi>Count,</hi> but I could not come ſooner, having been obliged to ſee the King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, who is gone toly Three Leagues from hence upon a Hunting match that is to be made to Morrow. I had like to have broak my word with you, added ſhe, for it is very late, and I muſt retire in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Have you only done me ſo great
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:61828:61"/>an Honour, Madam, anſwered <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> to deprive me of it ſo ſoon. What I ſuffer, purſued he ſighing, ſince Five or Six daies, cannot be ſollaced by ſo ſhort a happineſs. You ought not to complain, replyed the Queen, you have paſſed thoſe daies pleaſantly enough, of which you ſpeak; and if any thing has given you pain, it was without doubt my preſence, which has ſometimes troubled you in your ſofteſt moments. You, Madam, replyed the <hi>Count,</hi> can you diſturb my daies in that manner? Can you beleive it, No, I have ſeen it, ſaid the Queen, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual cares you take to fly me and ſhun my ſight, have but too often confirmed me in what I ſay. You take pleaſure, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, replyed the <hi>Count,</hi> to Laugh ſtill at my troubles. For it is not poſſible that you have not penetrated into all this fiction; and that notwithſtanding all my Artifice, my Eyes have not told you, that it was not without an extream vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that I forced my ſelf from you, and that I deprived my ſelf of ſeeing you. But how can you accomodate, replyed the Queen what you ſay, with the Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that you dayly made to the Counteſs?
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:61828:61"/>Is it ſtill a violence, or a habit of Cajole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to act with all the paſſionate part? I, Madam, interrupted the <hi>Count,</hi> with an air the moſt ſurprized imaginable, at the Proteſtations of the Counteſs? Yes you: replyed the Queen. There is not a Day you do not ſpend your ſelf in cares and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, for the expreſſing to her the greatneſs of your Love. Not that, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued ſhe, in an indifferent manner, I find fault with it. You know, added ſhe, that I was the firſt that counſelled it you, but why to be ſo difficult? What reaſon have you to deſire to abuſe the Credulity of a Princeſs, who has ever had goodneſs and eſteem enough for you, for your being obliged, to put ſome more confidence in her: muſt you needs by ſo baſe a Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry make her divine, what you take ſo much pains to conceal from her. <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> has told me enough of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion you made him; and it is ſuch a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val as he you ought to diſtruſt and not ſuch a Friend as I. And I do diſtruſt, Madam, that cruel Rival, interrupted la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably the ſad <hi>Hannibal,</hi> who has made me but too well comprehend the height of his happineſs. But is it him, purſued
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:61828:62"/>he, that you ought to beleive, Madam, when he ſpeaks againſt me? and that he gives you to underſtand that I am in Love with the Counteſs, ought not he to be content with the ſacrifice that you made him of my paſſion, without adding falſe reaſons to render it juſt? Of the Sacrifice, replyed the Queen much aſtoniſhed, that I make him of your paſſion? Yes, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, purſued the jealous <hi>Count,</hi> his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion having moved him to go and Triumph to the Counteſs of the laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation I had with you, that Lady has had the Cruel pitty.—He ſtopped there, ſurprized to ſee on a ſuddain the Counteſs appear before them, who came from behind a Hedge, which Compoſed the Alley they walked in. The Queen, as may be beleived, was in no leſs aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than he, not expecting to have ſo near her, the Perſon of the World ſhe ought moſt to fear, in ſuch a diſcourſe as ſhe had with the <hi>Count.</hi> The jealous Counteſs had obſerved in her Chamber certain raies of joy, in the Eyes of <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> from the moment of the ſecret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation he had had with the Queen, which had made her not only conjecture,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:61828:62"/>but all moſt divine that her Propheſie was truer than ſhe was willing it ſhould, and that the Queen went towards the <hi>Count</hi> when he made ſhew of flying her. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſeeing them both go out with the countenance of People, whoſe mind was full of ſome deſign, and eſpecially the <hi>Count,</hi> who, what violence ſoever he uſed, had not been able to conceal the uneaſineſs he was in that Chamber; ſhe rid her ſelf as ſoon as ſhe could of <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> and having ſent two Maids in whom ſhe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to obſerve the Queens ſteps, ſhe had no ſooner learnt that ſhe was gon into the Garden, accompanied only with two of her Maids of Honour, than that ſhe ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected a Rendevouze, wherein all that her jealouſie had been able to invent for the diſuniting of thoſe Two Lovers was going to be deſtroyed. She called for her Cloathes, and notwithſtanding all the oppoſition of the Perſons about her, who were aſtoniſhed at her deſign, and who repreſented to her that ſhe was not in a Condition to riſe; and much leſs to go out of her Chamber, and to go take the Air, ſhe would go walk in the Garden, and took with her only one of her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:61828:63"/>Maids, who was of her Confidence. She had not had the patience to be quite dreſſed, and all in diſorder ſhe deſcended into the Garden with more haſte than the weakneſs of her Body could well permit her, but it was the mind which carryed her, or if you will her Love or jealouſie. She had no ſooner diſcovered where the Queen was, than that ſtealing from Alley to Alley, and ſtill concealing her ſelf with the Hedges between which ſhe walked, ſhe came towards that where they were, and juſt in the time that thoſe two Lovers were going to informe themſelves upon her Chapter. Which obliged her to ſhow her ſelf, notwithſtanding all the Curioſity ſhe had of liſtening to them. It is true, that ſhe came to them with ſo much trouble and Agitation of mind, that ſhe could hardly underſtand what they ſaid. But in fine the Word of Sacrifice, and that of Counteſs coming to her Ears, ſhe could no longer be Miſtreſs of her ſelf: and muſt needs go interupt them. She did at firſt all ſhe could to compoſe her ſelf, but the alteration there was in her Face, did but too much diſcover the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of her coming in a place, where there
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:61828:63"/>was ſo little reaſon to expect her: and ſeeing the ſurprize with which they look'd upon her, you find it without doubt ſtrange, Madam, ſaid ſhe to the Queen, to ſee me here; and I am aſſured you did not expect me, but wearied with lying in Bed, I fancied it would do me no hurt to go take the Air. But may be I am come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniently and am troubleſome to you: If it be ſo, Madam, I ſhall retire. You ſpake, anſwered the Queen, ſomething bluſhing, a Language very new both to your ſelf and me. You know, purſued ſhe, that I am very glad to ſee you where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I am, and that you cannot incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mode me, but it is true, that I am ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing aſtoniſhed, that you have ſo little care of your health, and if there is any thing I blame in you, it is that. Nothing preſſed you to come out, but let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, for I confeſs you raiſe my pitty, and I fear you will really fall ſick. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, after having thanked the Queen for the tender Sentiments ſhe ſeemed to have for her, ſet her ſelf to follow her, but with ſo much difficulty, that ſhe could hardly bear her ſelf up, inſomuch that that Charming Princeſs, who had a moſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:61828:65"/>compaſſionate and tender Soul, taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, would not augment the ills of that Poor Sick Lady, and bid the <hi>Count</hi> have pitty of that Lover, and that he ſhould give her his Hand, reſolving that for once at leaſt the paſſion ſhe had in her Heart ſhould not be the ſtrongeſt. The <hi>Count</hi> obeyed, but the Converſation he had with that Lady was not great; for ſhe could hardly ſpeak, overcome with emotion that her Soul as well as her Body ſuffered. She only held her Eyes ſixed upon him, and it was the Language with which ſhe expreſſed to him all the violent motions, which then paſſed in her, and of which he was the only cauſe. They came in that manner to the Queens apartment, who, having been willing to accompany the Counteſs to her Chamber, left her, a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after, at the Liberty to go to Bed, of which ſhe had great need. The <hi>Count,</hi> having given her his Hand to lead her back, was in an extream impatience of entering again into the Converſation they had begun in the Garden, and which he perceived was tending to a kind Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation; But the Queen whether out of Malice or Prudence told him, that it was
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:61828:65"/>too late, and that he ſhould go give ſome Comfort to that deſolate Lady, and that they would at another time end their Quarrel. <hi>Hannibal</hi> undone with this anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, begged of her to give him at leaſt one Quarter of an Hours Audience more: but with an Air ſo paſſionate, that the Queen could not hold from laughing. You have then a mind, ſaid ſhe to him, to kill that Poor wretch, who at this Hour imagines a Thouſand things that ſting her. Go, purſu'd She, ſtill ſmiling, go put her Mind at reſt, for you owe this at leaſt to her Love. The <hi>Count</hi> looked upon the <hi>Queen,</hi> who he ſaw took delight in railling him upon his pain, and with an Air very indifferent; there are, <hi>Madam,</hi> anſwered he Her, other people about her who are more proper than I to render her thoſe Cares: But if her Diſeaſe had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for mine, her recovery would be very dangerous. You are too cruel, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the <hi>Queen,</hi> and that does not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch a man as you. But can it be poſſible, purſued She, that theſe are your true Sentements, and do you not ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe me? For after the things you daily ſay to the <hi>Counteſs,</hi> who certainly loves
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:61828:64"/>you very tenderly, your Soul muſt be full of Treachery that ſo much Contempt and Indifference can be without diſguiſe. The <hi>Count,</hi> whoſe Heart was pierced with all theſe Words the <hi>Queen</hi> ſaid to Him, though She ſpoke to Him in a manner, to make him know, that She was not fully perſwaded of what She reproached Him, hardly knew with what Air to anſwer her; but ſighing, What is it I beſeech you, Madam, I have ever ſaid to that Lady, that is contrary to the Sentiments I have alwaies made appear for you? Upon what have I entertained her, but of the tender paſſion, I have had more then Five Years for the moſt cruel Princeſs upon the Earth, and of which I muſt dye, for her ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If it is a Crime, purſued he to have made her this Confeſſion, which never ought to come out of my Mouth, accuſe the vanity, not to ſay the inſolence of <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> from whom ſhe had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy known all the Converſation I had had with you in your Chamber. What do you mean by <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> interrupted the Queen? This is the Third time you have mentioned him, without my compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending any thing of what you tell me.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:61828:64"/>Has he ever had part, purſued ſhe, in our diſcourſes: and muſt you not be very extravagant, or the Counteſs very wicked, to make you beleive, that I could be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of bringing him into ſuch a confidence, he who I ſhould fear in ſuch an occaſion more than all the Perſons of the World? But, Madam, interrupted the <hi>Count,</hi> why then was he hid in your Cabinet? Hid in my Cabinet, replyed the <hi>Queen</hi> ſtung with this Reproach, O, Heavens! and this is all the miſtery of this Sacrifice, and of that victime that I could not unriddle! and is it poſſible you could be perſuaded of ſo much baſeneſs on my part, you who ought to know me better than any Body. Go, If I did well, added ſhe, I ſhould leave you in your error; but I am too much concerned. The anger the Queen was thereupon in againſt the <hi>Count,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving almoſt calmed all the diſtruſt of that Lover, he fell upon his Knees to ask her Pardon, when of a ſuddain there entred one of the Counteſſes Women, who came to beg the <hi>Queen</hi> on her part, that She would oblige the <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> to paſs one moment in her Chamber before he went out of the Palace. The <hi>Queen</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:61828:66"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:61828:66"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:61828:67"/>being in extream vexation that that Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had ſound the <hi>Count</hi> in the poſture ſhe had ſeen him, would repair it by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him go that moment to the ſick, that She might not become quite deſperate: It was to ſend a man to Execution, by ſo much the more ſevere to the Amorous <hi>Hannibal,</hi> for that he ſaw himſelf in a fair way of reconciling His Affairs with the <hi>Queen.</hi> He muſt however obey, but after what manner ſo ſadly and with ſo much pain, that he raiſed pity in that char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Princeſs, who gave him not ſo harſh an Order, without being the firſt that found it ſevere. The Counteſs was in great joy to ſee that Lover return; but that joy was diſſipated by the meaſure She ſpake to Him, for his Anſwers were of a man ſo abſtracted, that She perceived that His Mind as well as His Heart was elſewhere while that his Body was with Her. Nothing cauſes ſo much vexation as theſe kind of abſences, eſpecially in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Women. This <hi>Lady</hi> was high ſpirited, and would not make the <hi>Count</hi> obſerve that She perceived His contempt; but the Converſation became barren at length: She was weary with maintaining
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:61828:67"/>it all alone. The Ambaſſador made no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Anſwer than Yes, and No, and would even two or three times have took leave of Her, under pretext that He feared to incommode Her. At which She growing impatient in the end, and ſuffering Her vexation to evaporate in Reproaches, She mnde him ſeveral She had no reaſon to make him, She attributed to Him Crimes the <hi>Count</hi> had never committed againſt Her; and in ſine, She threatned to ruine Him with the King, if He had not more Complaiſance for Her: Inſomuch that the <hi>Count</hi> knowing Her Spirit, and fearing this Point, by reaſon of the <hi>Queen,</hi> more than any thing that jealous Lady could have invented, very prudently reſolved to ſtay with her, and even to be more ſweet than He would have been, for the endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bring Her to Reaſon. The <hi>Queen</hi> according to the Cuſtom of Women who love well, was uneaſie, knowing Her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with her Rival, though She was well perſwaded, that She had the better part in his Heart, had reaſon to ſee Her Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions augmented, ſince that Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was to have laſted but a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was ſo long. She knew not in what
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:61828:68"/>pain poor <hi>Hannibal</hi> was; and her Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſuch as another Womans would have been in her place; that is to ſay, that He found Himſelf well with the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs,</hi> and that it was a Treachery She ought not to pardon Him, after he had pretended ſo to ſlight that Lady.</p>
            <p>Amongſt all theſe Diſquiets and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions, there was likewiſe Reaſons of Modeſty, that the <hi>Count</hi> was ſo late and ſo long in Her Apartment, contrary to the Cuſtom of that Court, and the King's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Orders, who would not ſuffer there any man but Himſelf, from Sun-ſetting to Sun riſing; and however the Night was very much advanced, which might make Her Maids and other people talk, who ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Her, and who might have believed that it was for Her ſake, and not the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſes, that that Ambaſſador ſtaid there at that unſeaſonable Hour: or at leaſt blame her for not putting her Lady of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in mind of her duty; But the means to do it, without making her jealouſie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to her Rival, who perhaps would have made a Triumph of it. She would rather have dyed than have given her the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In that perplexity of Heart and mind
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:61828:68"/>w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was great enough whether from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out or within, ſhe was told that the King was upon his return. This news did not at all ſurprize her. She was uſed to thoſe kinds of Caprichio's, which often took that Prince. But that which caſt her into a terrible uneſianeſs, was what would become of the <hi>Count:</hi> Who at the hour it was, could not go out but in paſſing by the Kings Attendants, who could not have failed to have known him which undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably expoſed her to ruine by a Prince ſo jealous and paſſionate as he was. It was not a time for her to balance any longer, if ſhe ought to go diſturb an entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which made Her more in paine than all the reſt, She had a better pretexte for it than ſhe could have deſired. In what danger ſoever we are, the leaſt ill we find on the ſide of Love is ever what we are moſt ſenſible of: ſhe therefore went without noiſe to the <hi>Counteſſe's</hi> Chamber, beleiving to ſurprize them in a very paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate entertainment, and which would convince the <hi>Count</hi> of perſidiouſneſs of which he could no longer defend himſelf, but ſhe was agreeably deceived in Her opinion, when entring the Chamber, ſhe
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:61828:69"/>found all in ſilence, with cold meenes on both ſides, from which one could not gueſs a very great tenderneſs. One part of the jealous motions of that <hi>Princeſs</hi> were then appeaſed, though ſhe had no great ſubject of joy, ſhe could not hinder her ſelf from appearing in good humour, and told them, almoſt laughing, what brought her thither. <hi>Hanibal</hi> and the Ladies could hardly perſwade themſelves it, but as the <hi>Queen</hi> fell to ſpeake then a little more ſeriouſſy and told them that there was no time to loſe if they would ſave themſelves from a miſfortune which would ruine them all three together, they thought of finding ſome expedient for the hiding the <hi>Count,</hi> not ſeeing that it was poſſible to lett him out of the appartment that night, without his meeting with ſome of the <hi>Kings</hi> people and perhaps the <hi>King</hi> himſelf. As they were each for their own intereſts, the <hi>Counteſs</hi> fancied there was no place ſo ſure as the ſhutting him in the Guard robe that was in her Chamber, and the <hi>Queen</hi> perceiving that if he were any where elſe that jealous one would be ſo uneaſy as might bring them into trouble, or at leaſt would imagine a thouſand things to her
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:61828:69"/>diſadvantage, agreed to it, and went out a moment after, for to ſend to ſee, where the <hi>King</hi> was, that if there was any opportunity of making the <hi>Count</hi> evade, the occaſion might not be loſt. That lover who was not content with the reſolution they had taken, of making him paſs the night in the <hi>Counteſſes</hi> Chamber, for whom he could not any longer but have an aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, followed the <hi>Queen,</hi> and told her, that ſhe ſhould rather condemn him to die by a thouſand hallebards, or caſt himſelf headlong out of the window, than to oblige him to ſtay ſo long with a Woman, whoſe ſight alone was become more inſupport able to him than Death it ſelf. The <hi>Queen</hi> turning towards him, and from whence comes it, <hi>Count</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, as if ſhe had been ſurprized at this diſcourſe, you have ſo much averſion after ſo long a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and which ought not to produce only contrary effects; If there has been any diviſion, purſued ſhe ſmiling, you will have leaſure to reconcile this Night; for Quarrels between lovers laſt not long, and it is uſually what moſt unites them. I have no Quarrel with her, anſwered the <hi>Count</hi> couldly, no more then I have ever
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:61828:70"/>had union: But what pleaſure do you take, purſued he in tormenting me with with that. You know whether my ſighs go, aded he, in looking upon her amorouſly, you know to whom my vowes are addreſſed, why ſhould you kill me by ſo cruel a way, for I declare to you, Madam, that if any thing has contributed to the averſion I have taken for that Lady, it is the unjuſt and diſobliging War you have daily made me upon her account. The <hi>Queen</hi> fell a laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the reſt of the converſation would have been favourable enough for the <hi>Count,</hi> for this <hi>Princeſs</hi> was ſatisfied with him that evening, but ſhe had notice brought her that the <hi>King</hi> was coming in: Inſomuch that ſhe had only time to tell that Lover, that he muſt return to the <hi>Counteſs,</hi> and to run to meet that <hi>Prince</hi> for the giving the <hi>Count</hi> leizure to retire. It was not poſſible for <hi>Hanibal</hi> to obey this order; the leſs ſince that the <hi>Queen</hi> did not ceaſe to charge him upon the <hi>Counteſſes</hi> account, he believed to be in right of ſeeking all meanes not to give her any longer reaſon to do it. He therefore ſought where he could hide himſelf in that chamber, and finding by chance that the <hi>Queen</hi> had left
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:61828:70"/>the Key in her Cabinet, he fancied that the Conjuncture was fair, that he ought to lay hold of it, and that he ſhould apparently be in more ſafety in that place than in any other part: Inſomuch that without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any noiſe, he ſlipt into it with the greateſt joy imaginable; and hearing the King already in the Chamber, he remain'd for ſome time planted in one and the ſame place, for fear, not knowing what was in the Cabinet, he ſhould have met with ſomething in the dark that might have made a noiſe and diſcovered him. The Dialogues there was between the K. and the Queen, and of which he loſt not one word, was for ſome time his Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the Courtſhip that Prince made uſe of for to Cokes his Dear Spouſe, was ſomething very pleaſant: but being at length wearied with ſtanding in one place, which demanded ſo much conſtraint, and where he had been already a long time, and no longer hearing any one ſpeake in the Chamber, he conjectured, that the King was already in Bed and was a ſleep, wherefore he would venture a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with deſign to open a Window that he might have a little light, if poſſible.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:61828:71"/>Whereupon he approached it, and as he ſought for the Caſement, he met with ſomething colder and ſofter than the Walls, or the Tapiſtry. His Curioſity went farther, and in fine by much feeling, he found the figure of a Man. He neither loſt time nor judgment, but taking his Ponyard in his Hand, he asked who it was, no anſwer was made him. He ſet his Weapon upon the mans Breaſt, and threatned him with Death, if he did not ſpeak. The Complement was ſomething harſh to a man who had no mind to dye ſuch a violent Deaths; Wherefore it had the effect that he deſired. For his Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard being ſet upon that Humane Body, cauſed immediately a lamentable voice, which ſaid to him, Ah! my Lord, take pitty of a wretch. In the emotion the <hi>Count</hi> was, he could not well diſtinguiſh that voice. Inſomuch that ſtill preſſing him to tell who he was, and what he came to do there. It is <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> my Lord, anſwered he, Ah! Traytor, the jealous <hi>Hannibal</hi> interrupted him with more fury than ever, is this a place for thee, he was in that moment ſo tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with rage, that he was Two or Three
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:61828:71"/>times upon the point of diſpatching a man ſo fatal to his repoſe, but in ſine a certain return of tenderneſs, that he had ſtill for that unjuſt Princeſs, ſtopping his arm, not doubting but that an action of that Conſequence would abſolutely ruin her, he ſpared for the Love of her the Blood of that wretch, and in ſuch a weight of grief not being able to ſtay any longer in that fatal Cabinet, leaſt his fury might perhaps at length overcome, the regards he owed, to what he ſo much loved, he went out, and paſſing without any noiſe through the King's Chamber, where there was no light, he went to the Counteſs, who was much ſurprized to ſee him; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the Queen who had but juſt left her, had proteſted ſhe knew not what was become of him; and that he muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely have been retired, without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing however after what manner, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeen him ſince the King was entred her Chamber. The <hi>Count</hi> who was as ſunk into deſpair, hardly hearing what<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that Lady ſaid to him, gave her no anſwer In the mean time, the Queen, in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſineſs ſhe was for her Lover, having heard ſome noiſe in her Cabinet, roſe ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:61828:72"/>while that her Husband repoſed in a profound ſleep, took her Night Gown, and would go ſee what it was, almoſt doubting the truth, that the <hi>Count</hi> had hid himſelf in that Cabinet. She advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced trembling towards the Door which ſhe found open, the <hi>Count</hi> not having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven himſelf the trouble to ſhut it for his Rival. But when ſhe was to have gone in, her courage failed her: ſeveral reſlections ſhe made all at once upon her ſelf, upon the time and the Hour it was, upon the Equipage ſhe was in in the dark, in a Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net where ſhe did not doubt but that her Lover was, but a Lover beloved, and againſt whom ſhe eaſily perceived that all her Glory could not reſiſt if he added vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; all theſe Reflections, I ſay, made her reſolve to return, rather than to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that cruel Glory to ſo evident a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: but ſhe was no ſooner near her Old Husband, who was in a deeper ſleep than ever, than that inſpired again with an amorous Curioſity, ſhe reproached her ſelf with her fearfulneſs, and arming her ſelf with new courage that her Heart ſuggeſted to her for the better deceiving her, ſhe went into that Cabinet without
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:61828:72"/>hearkening any longer to any Reflection, ſhe ſearched on all ſides, and ſuffering her ſelf to be led by a paſſion that blinded her, ſhe came at length to the place where <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> was, who knew not what to do, and had already curſed a Thouſand times the moment, he began to be in Love. The Queen, who in the different paſſions which ſhe was agitated with, could not fail of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much diſturbed, having loſt her Speech as ſoon as ſhe found what ſhe ſought, was ſome time ſilent, leaning upon that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, as a Perſon ready to faint. After which recovering her former forces, Ah! my Lord, ſaid ſhe to him, ſighing, to what do you expoſe me, you who know the Counteſſes Humour, and the King's jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Spirit, what do you do here; have you a deſign to ruin me? <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> to whom theſe words might be addreſſed as well as to the <hi>Count,</hi> not doubting but that the Queen had learnt from him, that he was in her Cabinet, ſell upon his Knees to that Princeſs, and embracing her, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Madam, ſaid he to her ſoftly, a Lover in deſpair, whom jealouſie has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated into this misfortune. The Queen had no ſooner diſcovered by the voice
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:61828:73"/>that it was not the <hi>Count,</hi> that already half dead for fear, ſhe fell into a ſwoon upon that Miniſter, who was not a little perplexed at this new misfortune. He knew not how to help that Princeſs, he ſaw that by the leaſt noiſe he ſhould make, his Life was gone, and in this perplexity he was bereft of all his Sences, and loſing courage, was likewiſe upon the point of falling into a ſwoon: When the Queen recovering her Spirits, who ſoever you are, ſaid ſhe to him, with a voice, that could hardly expreſs one word, ſave the honour of a Princeſs, who does not deſerve to be expoſed to ſo much ſhame. <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> fancied, that the fear, ſhe was in, diſturbed her Mind, and to encourage hir he asked her if ſhe knew not her antient and faithfull ſervant. The <hi>Queen</hi> then diſcovered who it was and not knowing if it was by the <hi>Kings</hi> order that he had hid himſelf in that Cabinet, ſhe treated him more gently than ſhe would have done. This Miniſter not knowing the <hi>Queens</hi> thoughts, avowed to her, that the jealouſie, he had of the <hi>Count,</hi> had brought him into that Cabinet, and in the deſpair the Counteſs had
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:61828:73"/>put him in that day, he had not been Maſter of himſelf, for to conſult the reaſon, or the reſpect he owed her. But was it of my Cabinet, ſaid the <hi>Queen</hi> you ought to make a place of retreate for the clearing your ſuſpitions! No, Madam, anſwered he, but if it is a crime, I might plead for pardon, ſince I aſſure you, I have been enough puniſhed by the hazard my life has been in from the <hi>Count's</hi> hands, who held his Ponyard a long time upon my throat, and ſtill more by the extream grief I am in for having cauſed ſo much trouble to the beſt <hi>Princeſs</hi> upon the earth. The <hi>Queen</hi> thereupon interupting him, asked him how he came to be with the <hi>Count,</hi> and what reaſon that Lord had had to fall out with him to that point, being ſo much his friend. This Miniſter attributed the reaſon of it only to their Concurrence for the <hi>Counteſs,</hi> and then making the <hi>Queen</hi> ſome reproches upon the promiſes ſhe had made him of favou in his intereſts, which ſhe abandoned for the vowes of another, related to her all that had paſſed in that Cabinet. The <hi>Queen</hi> was enough ſatisfied that <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> had not penetrated farther into the <hi>Count's</hi> Deſigne: But ſhe
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:61828:74"/>eaſily judged, that ſhe ſhould find it difficult to undeceive that Lover, that <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> came not there vpon her account, having been allready more than once ſuſpitious of it. She bid this Miniſter be perſwaded, that it ſhould not be her fault, that he was not ſucceſsfull in his deſires, and having recommended to him ſilence, in which he had as much or more intereſt than ſhe, ſhe added, that he muſt wait till it was day to go out of her Cabinet, and that ſhe would come her ſelf to fetch him away; After which ſhe went into the <hi>Counteſſes</hi> Chamber, where ſhe hoped to learn news of hir Lover. That Lady no ſooner ſaw her than that reaching her hand to her out of the Bed by way of Careſs, fanſying that it had been ſhe who had ſent him back to her; you come Madam, ſaid ſhe to her, the moſt conveniently poſſible to comfort the moſt deſolate of all men, and from whom I have not been able to get one word, ſince he came here. The <hi>Queen,</hi> who had well foreſeen the effect that the rencounter of <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> in her Cabinet would produce in the <hi>Count's</hi> mind, was ſo touched with the poſture in which ſhe found him,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:61828:74"/>ſitting in a Chaire, his Head leaning upon both his Hands, endevouring to hide his grief by riſing when ſhe entered, that, without conſidering who ſhe was, ſhe approached him, and with eyes all moſt full of teares, I know, <hi>Count,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him ſoftly, not to be heard by the <hi>Counteſs,</hi> the ſubject of your diſcontent; but if you will hear me one moment. I am ſure to cure your mind of the unjuſt diſtruſt that has juſt ſurpriſed you. He! What can you tell me, Madam, interrupted that ſad Lover with a lamentable voice, but what will perfectly ruine me; It is too much for you, replied ſhe, ſomething ſtung at the manner he received the effects of her good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and if I had not forgot who I am, I ſhould not debaſe my ſelf ſo far, as to juſtifie my ſelf with a man to whom I owe nothing, and who will hardly hear my juſtifications. They would be uſeleſs Madam, replied he, after what I have ſeen. I ſpoke to the man, purſued he, and it is not without reaſon, Madam, that the <hi>King</hi> being toly this night out of the Pallace you would engage me to paſs it in this Chamber. The Reproach, that the fury and vexation of the jealous <hi>Hanibal</hi> had made her, ſo
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:61828:75"/>peirced the <hi>Queen</hi>'s heart, that on a ſudain overcome with a torrent of teares, ſhe had not the power to make him an anſwer, and fearing above all things, that her Rival ſhould diſcover her weakneſs, ſhe retired and went to Bed in a condition the moſt cruel and afflicting that a <hi>Princeſs</hi> who has an extreame deal of Glory, and Heart preingaged by a great paſſion, could be reduced to. The <hi>Counteſs,</hi> who what care ſoever ſhe had given her ſelf for to hear, what thoſe two Lovers ſaid, could never comprehend any thing of it, which might give her the leaſt knowledg of what paſſed, and of the ſubject of the new Diviſion that ſhe well perceived there was between them, had more impatience and curioſity then ever, to enter into the <hi>Count's</hi> confidence: But notwithſtanding all ſhe could do, that lover was obſtinate not to acquaint her with any thing of his affairs, and only told her, that before ſour and twenty hours where paſſed, ſhe might divine the better part in learning the news of his depart. Of your Depart, my Lord, replied the <hi>Counteſs</hi> more ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed then ever; and why, what has been done that obliges you to quit us ſo ſoon?
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:61828:75"/>is the <hi>Queen</hi> the cauſe of it! is it me? Speake, for there is not any thing, but what I would do to hinder it if it depend on me. No Madam, anſwered the <hi>Count;</hi> but I have already told you, that I ſhall not explain my ſelf further therein; you will know enough in time, and whatſoever is the cauſe, it ſuffices that I tell you, that I have a very great reaſon for what I do, and that from the moment I can get from hence, I will go give order for my embark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The <hi>Counteſs</hi> pierced to the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of her Soul with hearing this news, as well as ſhe had joy at the miſunderſtanding there was between the <hi>Queen</hi> and him, did all that ſhe could to make him change his reſolution; and told him in reſpect of her ſelf, the moſt moving things imaginable, that ſhe might take advantage of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union: but that is not all waies the beſt time, for the gaininga Heart, which is ſometim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s themore ſtrongly bound, when it is believed to be diſengaged by ſome prevention. The <hi>Count</hi> hardly hearkned to what ſhe ſaid, and his Soul more diſpoſed to motions of deſpair, than to ſentiments of tenderneſs, did not ſhow that fair Lover one ray of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, nor even a ſpark of complaiſance,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:61828:76"/>he was in an extreame impatience till day came; And he no ſooner ſaw the moment he could retire without danger, than that he took his leave of the Lady, leaving her as little ſatisfied with him as one could be, and enough for the putting an end to a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, if theſe contempts did not ſometimes rather augment Love than diminiſh it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> who had paſſed one of thoſe terrible nights, that Love takes delight in poyſoning with all that is moſt cruel and bitter no ſooner ſaw the <hi>King</hi> go out, but ſhe aroſe to go put <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> out of her Cabinet. This Miniſter, who had been as uneaſy in this place as ſhe in her Bed, fell again upon his knees as ſoon as he ſaw her, and with a pityfull look, and Heart truly contrite, he asked hir pardon for all the troubles he had given her. The Queen having made him riſe, told him, that all this was nothing in compariſon of the grief ſhe had, that the <hi>Count</hi> had found him thus by night in her Cabinet; and that if he would repair the fault he had commited, and render himſelf worthy of her pardon, he muſt go find him out, and relate to him the true occaſion of his being in that place, and endeavour to undeceive him of certain
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:61828:76"/>impreſſion, that he might have taken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, it being important for her glory that that Ambaſſador had better Sentiments of her, than ſo unlucky an accident might give him: <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> who, in another occaſion, would hardly have been perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to take upon him ſuch a meſſage, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſubmitted himſelf to this Order, too happy to be quit with this ſatisfaction, which he owed to the goodneſs alone of a <hi>Princeſs,</hi> whoſe reputation he had ſo much hazarded, and whom he had brought into a condition of having all the reaſon imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to complain of, and to ruine him, as ſhe might have done if ſhe had a mind; at leaſt according to his opinion; but Affairs went quite otherwiſe than he believed, wherefore he promiſed to the Queen to execute faithfully what ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him, and having quitted her with great acknowledgment for her goodneſs, he went directly from thence to the Ambaſſadors Palace, where he found that all diligence poſſible was made for his depart; and that the <hi>Count</hi> having paſſed the night very ill, would not ſee any body that day, at leaſt till it was very late.</p>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:61828:77"/>
            <p>The Queen ſtayed in her Cabinet, loaded with thoughts upon which ſhe formed a thouſand deſignes, that the reſolutions ſhe made, upon the ſtate of her heart, inſpired her, when ſhe ſaw one of the <hi>Count's</hi> Pages enter her Chamber, who delivered her a Letter from his Maſter; ſhe opened it trembling, and the impatience the had at firſt to Read it, not permitting her to think of any thing elſe, the King, who was ever liſtning and ſpying her actions, entered the chamber at that time, and ſlipping ſoftly into the Cabinet, came upon her, before ſhe hardly, with the earneſſneſs ſhe read that Letter, perceived him, and ſnatched it out of her hands, without her being able to hinder it. The grief as well as ſurprize of that <hi>Princeſs</hi> were ſuch as may be eaſily imagined. She ran after the King begging him in the moſt earneſt and moving manner poſſible to reſtore her Letter, employing even tears but the more preſſing ſhe was, the ſuſpicions of that jealous Prince the more augmented: inſomuch that to be freed from the Queens importunity, he retired to his own apartment, where he might read that Letter with a little more liberty. I
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:61828:77"/>leave you to think in what a terrible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity the poor Queen was, that a Letter of the greateſt and moſt dangerous concern in the world was fallen into his hands, whom ſhe had moſt reaſon to fear; of a King jealous and paſſionate, and that in fine there was no means of having it again. She knew not what to do in ſo cruel a conjuncture, and her mind floating between fear and danger, love and ſhame, ſhe meditated an infinite number of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, without having the Courage to undertake any: ſhe went in ſine to the <hi>Counteſs</hi> to ask her councill, ſhe had formerly found it ſucceſsful; but it was now no longer the time. She firſt related to her, what had paſſed that night in her Cabinet between the <hi>Count</hi> and <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> and afterwards the misfortune that had happened to her upon the Letter, the <hi>Count</hi> had wrote to her upon that adventure. The diſſembling Counteſs overjoyed at ſo unlucky an accident, and that things were ſo diſordered, affected the ſhewing the Queen an extreame regret for that accident, but inſtead of comforting her, ſhe only told her things to make her the more deſpair, making her fear the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:61828:78"/>terrible conſequences of that Letter; and that if ſhe did not take refuge with the ſooneſt in ſome Convent, ſhe would find the fatal conſequences it would be of to her. The ſad deſolate Princeſs ſuffering her ſelf to be perſwaded to follow that advice, as it really was the ſafeſt, tho the Counteſs gave her that council to be rid of her, to have the more liberty of taking, according to what ſhould happen, ſuch meaſures, as her Love, or rather her deſpair ſhould adviſe her: The Queen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay reſolved to go caſt her ſelf into a Convent, for avoiding the Kings fury, quitted the Counteſs and prepared her ſelf to execute with the ſooneſt her deſigne. During this, <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> who had not been able to procure to ſpeak with the Ambaſſador of <hi>Naples,</hi> returning to his Houſe found people, who told him, that the King had cauſed him to be ſought for every where. Is it not, ſaid he immediately to himſelf, that he knows that I have paſſed the night in the Queens Cabinet? Every man, whoſe conſcience is ulcerated with any crime of which he cannot juſtifie himſelf, is ever in fear of being accuſed of it. He took courage however and went
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:61828:78"/>to that Prince, who was alon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in a by cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, walking apare and with a paper in his hand. Well, ſaid he to him ſo ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n as he ſaw him, is it thus. Traytor, that thou takeſt care of my honour! are theſe purſued he with a thundring voice in ſhowing him that paper or Letter, the Orders that I gave you, when I recomended her to thy care! by Heavens, thou ſhalt ſmart for it. This poor Miniſter, as ſoon as he heard the King ſpeak with this fury, did not doubt, but that the Queen had told him all, and caſting himſelf immediately upon his knees, and with a lamentable voice, Ah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir, ſaid he to him, Heaven is my Witneſs, that I never in my life had any deſire that was contrary to your glory, and that it would be very eaſy to make appear my innocence if moderating your anger a little you would be graciouſly pleaſed to give me one moment of audience. And what canſt thou ſay, interrupted the furious Monarch, to juſtifie what I have here? Is it not to be criminal, to ſavour the bold and infamous deſigns that the Ambaſſador of <hi>Naples</hi> has upon the Queen? I, Sir, favour ſo criminal deſigns, replied <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> who begun to be a little bold. Yes! thou, replied that
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:61828:79"/>Prince, how can I interpret otherwiſe the Stories thou daily toldſt me, that he lived very reſpectfully with the Queen, while they have ſecreet practices together? Can any other ſerve that Ambaſſador in this? and is it not viſible thou art of intelligence with them to deceive me? All that you tell me, Sir, replyed the Miniſter, ſurprizes me, and I know not, if I ſhould tell you that in regard of that Ambaſador you may be miſtaken. Ah perfidious man! cryed the King tranſported with rage, thou wouldeſt continue to abuſe me! thou hadſt beſt deny it: I have herewith to confound thee: See the inſolent teſtimony of that infamous man, which but too well declares my diſhonour, and afterwards tell me if my ſuſpicions are juſt, and if I have reaſon to accuſe thee; thou muſt, purſued he, explain to me all the myſtery of that letter, or thou dyeſt. <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> took it trembling not doubting by what he heard the King ſay, that there was ſomething in it which concerned him, and found theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I ought to believe, Madam, that after the fatall incounter of laſt night, you will not be ſurpized at my depart. How cruel ſo
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:61828:79"/>ever the thing was, I do not complain of you. It is of my deſtiny and of Heaven that I will complain, for having made me caſt my eyes, to the unhappineſs of my days, upon a Princeſs it deſtinied for the love of another. A Preference ſo much the more cruel that the ſubject is low, and unworthy of being preferred to the leaſt of all men. This thought alone aſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates me; and I ſhould willingly at the price of a thouſand lives be ſtill in the error I was, and never to have entred that Cabinet, where I ſaw, what I never could have beleived. O Heaven! Can I yet think it, after having ſeen it? Farewel too unjuſt Princeſs. I quit you without regret, but it is to go paſs the reſt of my Life, as a man fuller of deſpair than Love.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Le C. d' A.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>D. Geronimo,</hi> who had thitherto beleived, that that Ambaſador was really in Love with the Counteſs of <hi>Palomer,</hi> was very much ſurprized with reading that letter; and haven taken courage, by his not being named in it, though he perceived, that it was of him the <hi>Count</hi> was jealous, he proteſted to the King, that he had never had the thought that
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:61828:80"/>the Ambaſſador of <hi>Naples</hi> had the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign upon the Queen, and that on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary he had alwaies beleived him in Love with the Counteſs of <hi>Palomer:</hi> in ſequel of which there had been ſome jealouſie between them upon that account, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for a Proof that their Intelligence was not great, it was above Eight Daies ſince he had ſpoke to him. That if he durſt take the Liberty to tell him, what he thought of that Letter, he beleived, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Title of Princeſs, it was addreſſed to the Counteſs rather than to the Queen. The King little ſatisfied with all theſe reaſons, would however read over that Letter again, for to ſee if there was any appearance of what his Miniſter told him, whom he had thitherto ſound very faithfull. But the particularity of that Cabinet too much referred to the Queen to attribute it to any other. That which moſt confounded the King, was this favoured Gallant, of whom the <hi>Count</hi> complained, not knowing upon whom to caſt his Eyes, there being no other than <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> of all thoſe of his Court to whom it was permitted to enter the Queens apartment: and there was ſo little
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:61828:80"/>appearance of caſting his conjectures upon ſuch a man as he, that, how ſuſceptible ſoever he was of jealouſie, it could not fall into his mind. He would however be cleared of the truth, and force the Queen to confeſs all things to him; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards take ſuch meaſures, as the reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch an injury ſhould inſpire him, and that the Guilty might repent their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence. He went with this deſign to that Princeſſes Chamber, cauſing <hi>Don Geroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> to follow him, and would not ſuffer him to quit him, till he had unfolded all this intrigue. He found her not there: and thereupon went to the Counteſſes, where he knew the Queen was moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, but found no Body there. He as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in a furious manner, what was become of the Queen. But could learn no news of her, he feared ſome other Treaſon: and was in a greater deſpair than ever. He threatned all thoſe he met, he ſent them to ſeek every where the Queen or the Counteſs, and nothing was heard but rumour through all the Palace: He learnt in fine, that the former was deſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Garden, and that the other was gone out of the Palace in mans Cloaths. All
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:61828:81"/>this confounded him and increaſed his fear and uneaſineſs. He ran towards what moſt concerned him; which was the way the Queen had gone, and he was ſeen like a loſt man, who comes, who turns from one ſide to the other of the Garden, without being able to meet the Queen. All his People were frighted, he was ſo himſelf more than any one: and putting all the World in pain, he ſuffered the moſt cruel tortures that can be imagined. Notice was brought him that the Ambaſſador of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> prepared to depart, and he fancied to diſcover in that moment what ſo ſuddain and ſo ſecret a departure threatned him with. He gave orders to go ſtop that Ambaſſador, not doubting but that his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign was to carry away the Queen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He was told, that he was no longer at his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and that he was mounted on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back to go away with all thoſe of his Train. Thus, that Old <hi>Monarch</hi> falling into Exclamations that he was betrayed on all ſides, and commanding his Guard to take Horſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his faithfull Subjects ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in a Conjuncture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> concerned, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ented
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:61828:81"/>not the outrage, that was deſigned him.</p>
            <p>The Queen, after having taken Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Counteſs, reſolved to retire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Convent: and without loſing time, ſhe wrote this Note to the <hi>Count</hi> to demand his Comapny to Guard her, imagining ſhe might have need of it, in the few moments that were left her to get thither.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Letter you wrote is ſomething ſo cruel, that it would require more time than I have to make it an anſwer. It is ſufficient, that I tell you, that I know, who I am, and of what Blood I come, not to be capable of any ſuch crime you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me of. I ſhould not be in pain to juſtifie my ſelf; and I ſhould have much more to pardon you ſo cruel a ſuſpicion: but this is not a time for my juſtification, nor your puniſhment. Know only, that the King has taken your Letter from me, and that I am neceſſitated to take Refuge in a Convent, if I will avoid all that his fury is going to make him act upon me. Send me as ſoon as poſſible ſome of your People to conduct me to <hi>Majorca.</hi> I ſhall come out at the Garden back Door, where I ſhall be in a moment. Adieu! If poſſible, let me ſee you once more.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:61828:82"/>
            <p>As for the Counteſs, ſhe was no ſooner delivered from the Queen, than in the Conjuncture of all this diſorder, her Love inſpiring her with Romantick deſigns, ſhe ſent to ſeek for her Gentleman of the Horſe, in whom ſhe put great confidence, and having related to him in few words what paſſed, ſhe added, that ſhe would not be alone expoſed to the King's fury, from which ſhe did not at all doubt, that ſhe ſhould ſuffer the moſt violent effects, if the Queen went away, and ſhe ſtaid i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Palace. Inſomuch that it was requiſite notwithſtanding all her illneſs, that her Body ſhould take forces from the neceſſity of the time, and that ſhe diſpoſed to ſave her ſelf as ſoon as poſſible. This Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Horſe, very complaiſant to the wills of his Miſtreſs, having anſwered her, that he was ready to obey her, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all ſhe ſhould pleaſe to order him, ſhe cauſed a Gentleman's habit to be brought, which ſhe had made uſe of in a Maſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, and with which ſhe diſguiſed her ſelf. After which having cauſed two good Horſes to be brought ſome paces from the Palace, ſhe took what Money, and Jewels ſhe had, very neceſſary move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:61828:82"/>for the deſign ſhe meditated, and departed from <hi>Belver,</hi> accompanied only by that Gentleman of the Horſe, who was ſurprized, having ſeen her ſick in Bed, that on a ſuddain ſhe found her ſelf capable of ſitting on Horſe-back, ſo much power has Love upon Bodies, when it ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates the Heart.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Count,</hi> who, as we have already ſaid, had prepared for his depart, are ſinece the Morning he came from the Palace: his orders being but to ſtay at <hi>Majorca</hi> as long as he ſhould judge neceſſary for the reconciling the King and Queen, no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er received that Princeſſes Letter, than that making all his People take Horſe, he made them file off by little and little, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that ſide of the Garden ſhe had mentioned. Immediately his affliction was extream, notwithſtanding all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons he beleived he had to complain of her, for having thus cauſed the unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Princeſs, he ſtill loved too paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, with all the injuſtice ſhe had done him, not to intereſt himſelf, in all that concerned her. He went then to the place where the Queen expected him, being at the Head of all his People, and he
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:61828:83"/>no ſooner ſaw her, than on a ſuddain Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loping, towards that ſide, he alighted, and preſenting her with his own Horſe, he ſerved for her maſter of the Horſe, and one of his Gentlemen rendred the ſame Office to one of her Bed Chamber, who accompanied her. After which he diſpoſed his People in Three Troups, and placing himſelf with the Queen at the Head of that of the middle, they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched inceſſantly towards the City of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorca.</hi> Theſe two Lovers were ſome time in entertaning themſelves upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the conjuncture. The Queen, who notwithſtanding the unhappy Eſtate of her Affairs, thought her ſelf too happy to have got out of the Palace, could not hold from ſhowing an extream joy to ſee her ſelf in the midſt of ſo brave a Nobility, in whoſe looks ſhe ſaw a boldneſs, capable of driving away all manner of fear: eſpecially of <hi>Count Hannibal,</hi> who appeared to her handſommer that Day than he had ever been, and to have ſo warlike a meen, that he animated all the others. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſhe almoſt forgot, that this was a beginning of a Thouſand troubles that Fortune prepared her. They looked
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:61828:83"/>upon one another ſome time without ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing, each of them beleiving that it was for the other to begin the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and to make ſome ſort of repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: But the Queen, was too much concerned to undeceive the <hi>Count,</hi> of the falſe impreſſions he had taken upon the Subject of <hi>Don Geronimo,</hi> ſeeing that there was not a moment to loſe, at length broak ſilence. Well! <hi>Count,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, will you not ask Pardon for the Letter you wrote me this Morning? It is true, Madam, anſwered the <hi>Count,</hi> that I am the moſt unhappy of all men, to be the cauſe of all this diſorder: and that if I could repaire it by my Death, I would go immediately, offer my Head to the King of <hi>Majorca.</hi> That is not in what you are moſt criminal, replyed the Queen, and I ſhould not be in much pain to Pardon you this ſault, though it coſt me my Life. But, my Lord, added ſhe bluſhing, your unjuſt ſuſpicions, are ſo unbecoming a Princeſs of my cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and whoſe Glory has been able to reliſt the Inclination ſhe had for you, are theſe crimes that can be Pardoned? The <hi>Count</hi> hearkened to the Queen with a
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:61828:84"/>joy that tranſported him, and caſting a languiſhing look upon her. I confeſs, Madam, replyed he, that there is no tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but what I ſhould merit, if my ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions were ill grounded, but I have but too much wherewith to juſtify my diſtruſts, and maintain the reaſons I had to conceive them, by Teſtimonies that you cannot your ſelf diſavow. And what Reaſons and what Teſtimonies, replyed the Queen, ſomething diſpleaſed at this anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, have you? What to have found <hi>Don Geronimo</hi> in my Cabinet, where the jealouſie, he had of you upon the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſes account, hade made him hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, am I Guilty of all the extravagancies that it has pleaſed your fancy to Figure to it ſelf thereupon? Well, <hi>Count,</hi> added ſhe ſighing, if this Miniſter had pleaſed me enough for that, if I had loved him, I would have took ſuch order as you ſhould never have perceived it. I would not have ſlattered your Paſſion with any hopes as I have done: I ſhould not have ſought to ſee you in particular, and in fine the Paſſion that you might have had for the Counteſs, could not have been ſo uneaſie to me as it was. Once more,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:61828:84"/>
               <hi>Count,</hi> purſued ſhe, you are very much miſtaken, and you little deſerve all the efforts my Heart has made for the Love of you. Theſe Reflections ſoftning her Heart, her Eyes were filled with Tears, and ſhe was not able to purſue her diſcourſe. The words of that fair Princeſs having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt diſſipated the fears of that Lover, he could not ſee this effect of ſenſibility with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a confuſed tranſport of joy and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and viewing her with Eyes, which ſignified all this, ſhould it be poſſible, Madam, ſaid he to her, that with ſo much reaſon of loving you, I ſhould have none to complain of you. Ah, Heavens! purſued he, why ſhould I be ſo happy in the moment I muſt quit you. He had hardly finiſhed thoſe laſt words, than that the Gentlemen of his Troop made him ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that there came down a Body of Horſe from <hi>Belver,</hi> and that thoſe of their arrier Guard had already made a halt, to expect them. The <hi>Count</hi> having caſt his Eyes towards the place that was ſhowed him, did not doubt but that it was the Cavalry that the King ſent after them, for to ſtop them: Inſomuch that fearing, that thoſe that were behind, were not
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:61828:85"/>ſtrong enough to reſiſt them, he detached part of his Troop to go Second them, and ſent orders at the ſame time to thoſe of the Vaunt-guard to Face about, and to go joyn them alſo, while that he, with the few People he had, would accompany the Queen, to the place of her retreat: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that going a little Gallop, they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued their way as far as <hi>Majorca,</hi> of which they had then made more than the half. That Princeſs was ſo ſatisfied with ſeeing that ſhe was at length juſtified with the <hi>Count,</hi> and that ſhe had diſſipated all his falſe Ombrages, that ſhe was almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible to all the reſt, and all that ſhe feared was the moment ſhe muſt part from him, and which that Lover made the more ſenſible to her, by his ſaying to her, during all the reſt of the way, the moſt paſſionate things imaginable, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing the crime he had committed againſt her, in ſuſpecting her with ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le reaſon of ſo much baſeneſs. He would have perſuaded her to have gone aboard his Galleys, rather than to expect the danger with which ſhe was threatned, and he told her all manner of things that could make her take this courſe. But the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:61828:85"/>Queen ſeeing to what ſuch a flight would expoſe her Glory, and that ſhe could not repair it but in following her firſt deſign, begged of him not to tryumph over her weakneſs, and rather help her to bear ſo cruel a Separation, than to engage her in the taking a conduct ſo contrary to her Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. The kind things that they ſaid to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thereupon till that they arrived in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, where the Queen deſigned to ſhut her ſelf up, which was a Royal-Abbey, Three Hundred Paces from the City, were ſenſibilities that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Lovers may eaſily imagine, but which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be well deſcribed. That fair Princeſs had prayed the <hi>Count,</hi> that as ſoon as they were arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in that Abbey, he would quit her, without ſaying to her any thing, and that he would take care to embark with the ſooneſt, not to expoſe himſelf to the violences that the King might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. But that Lover could neither obey the one nor the other: and he no ſooner ſaw the Queen upon entring her retreat, than falling upon his Knees, his Eyes all bathed in Tears, he embraced hers with ſo much tranſport, that that tender Princeſs, uſing upon her ſelf an extream vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence for the overcoming the ſenſible motions, of ſo cruel a ſarewell, fainted in the Arms of Two Religious, who carryed her into the Convent, leaving that poor Lover ſo loſt in greif, that he was ſometime as not himſelf, without being able to part from that place. Nothing but ſobs and ſighs, which moved all thoſe who heard them, But in fine, the People he had about him, ſeeing there was no time to looſe for the ſecuring thoſe they had left behind them, put him in mind, that they might have need of his preſence. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:61828:86"/>that a little recovering from ſo ſad a ſtate, he took Horſe, and went with a great deal of pain from his dear Princeſs, turning inceſſantly his Head that way, not being able to go the rate his People went, without as it were racking his Heart. He arrived at length at the place where he had left all that Nobility, that had attended him in his engagement, and he found them almoſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the Number rather than the valour of the Enemies. The King was at their Head, who cauſed Troops to come inceſſantly to ſecond the former. The Count's was but few in compariſon of the others, but all warlike men, and who breathed in numbere nothing but Glory; They were a nima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted anew by the <hi>C.</hi> ſight, who falling upon the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorquins</hi> with a boldneſs that it ſeemed as if he had a powerfull Army with him, he repulſed them not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their Number as far back as under the Canon of <hi>Belver,</hi> and could have made the K. Priſoner, if the taking him could have been of any uſe to his victory: but the Q. being in a place of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and having nothing more to do, than to retire to his Galleys, he would not puſh his valour far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: he rallied ſuch of his people as were a little ſtrayed in that purſuite, and retired in ſo good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſo aſſured a countenance, that the <hi>Major<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quins</hi> never had the courage to purſue him: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that having gained the <hi>Port de Portopi,</hi> which is half a League from <hi>Majorca,</hi> to which place he had in the Morning ordered his Galleys to come he cauſed all his People to go on board, and falling to Rowing, in a little time they got out of ſight o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe Inſularies.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
